<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Conversations written in French by Monsieur Clerombault ; and put into English by a person of honour.</title>
            <title>Conversations. English</title>
            <author>Palluau, Philippe de Clérembault, comte de, 1606-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R914</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13170599</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13170599</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98279</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98279)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 412:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Conversations written in French by Monsieur Clerombault ; and put into English by a person of honour.</title>
                  <title>Conversations. English</title>
                  <author>Palluau, Philippe de Clérembault, comte de, 1606-1665.</author>
                  <author>Méré, Antoine Gombault, chevalier de, 1610-1684.</author>
                  <author>Person of honour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>156 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another translation published in 1677 as: Conversations of the Mareschal of Clerambault and the Chevalier de Méré.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Palluau, Philippe de Clérembault, --  comte de, 1606-1665.</term>
               <term>Méré, Antoine Gombault, --  chevalier de, 1610-1684.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Philosophy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:98279:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:98279:1"/>
Converſations WRITTEN IN FRENCH By <hi>Monſieur Clerombault,</hi> And put into ENGLISH</p>
            <p>By a Perſon of Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Herringman</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Blew Anchor</hi> in the Lower Walk of the <hi>New Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M DC LXXII,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:98279:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98279:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Was a long time known to the Marſhal of <hi>C.</hi> without having any familiarity with him, till (being withdrawn from Court, by reaſon of ſome indiſpoſition of health) he was about ſix months at <hi>Poictiers,</hi> where he endeavoured to perfect his recovery, and divert himſelf. I was in that Country when he came thither, and ſought on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to paſs my time as pleaſantly as I could. The Mareſhal had ſo agreeable a Wit, that every one was pleaſed with hearing him, which made me ſee him often, and it was my happineſs to have ſome ſhare in his friendſhip. He un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that his Friends at Court had deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to get an Imployment for him, which was the more honourable, becauſe Merit was the principal thing that was looked upon in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of it. And becauſe one could not be too careful in acquitting ones ſelf worthily in
<pb facs="tcp:98279:3"/>
an affair of that conſequence, he often thought upon it, and conſidered of it, and ſometimes ſpoke to me concerning it, under other colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able pretences. Not but that he had confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence enough in me to have diſcovered to me his moſt ſecret thoughts: But being yet uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the iſſue, he was not willing that any ſhould imagine that he was in expectation of it, leſt the thing ſhould not ſucceed. I partly knew his deſign, and he himſelf perceived it. Nevertheleſs he was willing to diſguiſe it (for the leaſt veil is a great help to modeſt perſons) he made ſome reflection upon thoſe that had been Conquerors, and asked me what I thought of them, and by what ways they were become ſuch great men, whether it were their Birth or Education, or both, nay whether Fortune might not pretend to have contributed. He loved <hi>Alexander,</hi> but admired <hi>Cæſar;</hi> and of two Perſons who had governed in our times, well known to him, he did value the height of the one, and the Art of the other, being well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to diſcourſe of eminent Perſons, he freely ſpoke his Judgment of them, and I obſerved by all his diſcourſe, that the King held the firſt place in his opinion. He was ſo charmed with this <hi>Prince,</hi> that he was almoſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported when he ſpake of him, and the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb facs="tcp:98279:3"/>
of his Air and good Meen gave him admiration; he told me that whoever ſaw him muſt love him; that he was the happieſt birth, had the beſt heart in the World; that as young as he was, his knowledge in things exceeded his; and that by a natural diſcernment he had an averſion to ſeigned honeſty, and could not endure baſe Compliance or unhandſom Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries. This methinks ſhould be ſufficient to make a Court of worthy honeſt men, and to produce a happy Age. The Mareſhal was a very good Judge of all this, and I knew by his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and manner of ſpeaking, that he was very well perſwaded of what he had ſaid; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, was it likely that he ſhould diſguiſe his thoughts to me, on deſign to be better received at the Court, or make any advantage by diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a perſon that goes not thither? Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of theſe Conquerors and Heroes, and conſidering what it was, went to the making up of great men, or rather what might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat an honeſt man (for that was what he deſigned) it happened that we ſpake almoſt of every thing: and as perfect honeſty is made appear by our actions as well as words, we judged of both, this Converſe laſted till his departure. After a certain tenderneſs which friendſhip inſpires at parting, when one has
<pb facs="tcp:98279:4"/>
ſpent ſo many days pleaſantly together (at leaſt on my part) he conjured me to conſider on our Diſcourſe, and told me, that he had a great deſire to write ſomething of them; and that if I on my part would alſo do ſomething, it would divert us at our meeting again. I writ five or ſix Converſations, and as I was about to proceed, I underſtood that his illneſs increaſed, and ſuddenly after I heard what beſel him.</p>
            <p>To conclude, there are ſome perſons in the World who endeavour to inform and perfect themſelves by reading, but the moſt part of them ſeek only after the pleaſure of it; and I blame them not, for I am partly of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; I ſhould deſire only that Juſtice might be done to every thing, and that as much may be diſcovered as is poſſible, and what we may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably expect on each Subject; for it cannot be imagined (be ones Art never ſo great) that we can extremely pleaſe when we write on thoſe Themes which tend to inſtruction. In effect, to diſcourſe a long time of Truths and of Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, of Good and Evil, is a kind of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment which agitates the mind without moving the heart; and that which commonly pleaſes proceeds from the contrary; for the heart ſhould be moved, and the mind undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed.
<pb facs="tcp:98279:4"/>
Beſides, although people are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be deceived, they love much leſs to be undeceived; and that (perhaps) is one of the chief reaſons why the World as yet knows ſo little, as to the benefit that may be made by reading theſe Entertainments. There are but few people who will believe that they ſtand in need of them, to render them either more knowing or able; but this is true, that the more Wit any one hath, the more he will like them, and it requires only a good ſenſe to underſtand them; Learning will help very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. It is likewiſe true, that the moſt worthy man by reflecting on them, will yet become more worthy; and that the moſt accompliſhed Lady, by imploying never ſo little time in them, will become more agreeable, and conſequently the more deſirable. It is ſo eaſie to be ſatisfied of this, that it would be great imprudence to affirm it without being certain of it. I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times raiſe my Subject, and ſometimes let it fall, the better to ſhew in every thing the good and the ill; for I deſign no praiſe to my ſelf.</p>
            <p>To conclude, I ſhould not have thought of writing theſe Converſations, if I had not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that I ſhould do a pleaſure to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of whom I have been ſpeaking. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, I apply my ſelf to nothing, and
<pb facs="tcp:98279:5"/>
not aim to appear publick, I underſtand well enough the different opinions of the World not to deceive my ſelf in them: the ſmalleſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which commonly is the beſt, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeldom found the ſtrongeſt; and if I had followed my own humour, and undertaken to write, it ſhould have been upon other Subjects.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98279:5"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>THE FIRST CONVERSATION.</head>
               <p>THE Mareſhal of <hi>C.</hi> is a Perſon juſtly deſerving the Character of a gallant Man, who underſtands the World perfectly well. He hath ſpent his time for the moſt part either at the Court or in the Army; and there are but very few who have had a greater ſhare than he of thoſe natural parts, which renders a man both able and agreeable. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his little impediment, he expreſſes himſelf gracefully; he loves rather to ſpeak than to hear others, whether it be that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſeldom anſwer his expectation, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as 'tis thought) that he takes delight to make himſelf admired. It is above two years ſince he began to be ill; all the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians who have been with him, and the Waters of <hi>Bourbon</hi> have not cured him: it is a diſtemper which hath not at all ſeized on his Spirits, for he never had them more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98279:6"/>
lively nor pure, nay nor more pleaſant. He was for ſome time with Madam <hi>Mareſchale</hi> to breathe (as they ſay) his native Air; but it ſeldom happens that a Courtier, who is ſick at the Court, can think himſelf bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at his Country-houſe. Madam <hi>Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chale</hi> was upon her return to <hi>Paris,</hi> and the Mareſhal came to <hi>Poictiers,</hi> where he was ſix or ſeven months; where-ever he is, he endeavours to divert himſelf, and delights to pleaſe others: and as there is nothing ſo inconſiderable, which a great man when he undertakes it, cannot ſet a value upon; the Mareſhal, knew ſo well how to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the leaſt occaſions of pleaſure, that where-ever he was, Divertiſement was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanting. One day finding himſelf bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than he uſed to be, he deſired the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of ſome Ladies at Dinner with him, which was not of thoſe kind of Feaſts, where many times there is nothing pleaſes but ſuch a delicate and ſo well choſen an Entertainment, that there was nothing more to be deſired. Ladies Meals common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are not very long, whether it be that they love not that kind of exceſs, or that they diſtruſt themſelves, and think they ſhould abate of that modeſty which gains
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98279:6"/>
them a reſpect. As ſoon as they roſe from Table, every one began to divide Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, ſome to play, others to look on. The Mareſhal, who was only a Spectator, ſpake according to his cuſtom many pleaſant things; but Play being imployment enough of it ſelf, and becauſe the Loſers commonly are not in humour to be delighted with Wit, he thought it beſt to ſay little, and to avoid the occaſion which tempts the moſt reſerved. He drew the Chevalier aſide, and going into another Room, You may eaſily believe (ſaid he) that I am very glad to ſee you, but I muſt aſſure you further, that I find my ſelf ſomething better for ſeeing you: and to ſay truth, after having try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo many remedies to recover me of an illneſs, which Melancholy would not at all leſſen, I have now nothing to ſeek after but Mirth.</p>
               <p>The Chevalier who ſtudied how to divert him, aſked him what he had moſt mind to do. I was more willing to entertain him, anſwered the Mareſhal than play with the Ladies, we will diſcourſe of certain things which are not commonly learned in the Commerce of the World. I never wiſhed any thing ſo much as that I were a little leſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98279:7"/>
ignorant, and when I converſe with you in particular, methinks I rid my ſelf of it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſtudy or inſtructions. The leaſt thing that you relate to me of <hi>Socrates</hi> ſinks very deep into my mind, and I hope one day I ſhall be heard to cite divine <hi>Plato</hi> as the Lady does who hath a good Wit, and delights very much to diſcourſe upon every thing. Wit (ſaid the Chevalier) is always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, and Women alſo in my opinion cannot have too much of it; but moſt people approve not of their being ſo knowing, or at leaſt that they ſhould ſhew it; and may not this Lady you ſpeak of, be the ſame who had given you the Idea of thoſe whom you repreſented ſo pleaſantly the other day. I never ſaw any thing better imitated nor more to my liking; without doubt it is not enough to have Wit, but he muſt be an extreme well-bred man that can know how to be pleaſant after ſuch a manner. I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with you, ſaid the Mareſhal that among perſons that know how to judge, one cannot be too well accompliſht to be as pleaſant as one would deſire, becauſe that moſt people have not a delicate taſte, nor are able to diſcern that which is beſt; it often happens that they are taken, nay even charmed with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98279:7"/>
certain ridiculous parts they play to them: but well bred perſons do not uſe ſuch kind of Buffonnery. You know very well that there are ſome perſons who are pleaſant Company, and who notwithſtanding are not beloved, and for whom few are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. I do not think that any one hath reaſon to envy ſuch kind of perſons: but thoſe who are pleaſant indeed after the beſt manner, never fail of gaining the heart, and 'tis in that way that I ſhould be glad to pleaſe. One cannot ſhew too much Wit in a pleaſant Converſation, yet one muſt have a care not to be too forward, as if you would appear always ready to make Jeſts, and ſpeak fine things: there is ſomething of a free eaſie way which cannot be expreſt, that has a better effect. Neither is it good to be too reſerved, nor affect ſingularity too much: when one is arrived to ſuch a degree of Merit, an open and complaiſant Carriage hath very great Charms to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract Love; what advantages ſoever any one hath, they muſt be pleaſed with others, if they would have others pleaſed with them. I obſerve that there are ſome Fooleries which are currant amongſt ſome people, which do not much credit thoſe that uſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98279:8"/>
them, they are rather the ſubject of ſcorn than laughter to thoſe that rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
               <p>They are laughed at, added the Chevalier as that Queen of <hi>Egypt</hi> laughed at the fine words and pretty conceits of <hi>Anthony.</hi> How, replied the Mareſhal that <hi>Anthony</hi> who was one of <hi>Cæſars</hi> Generals, who diſputed the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire with <hi>Augustus?</hi> Oh that pretty <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an!</hi> and what could ſhe find in him to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt. The Chevalier then giving him to underſtand, that it might be ſomething of bluntneſs, he being in Armor, and always dreſt Souldier-like, I ſee by that, anſwered the Mareſhal that there was in thoſe days your Virtuoſo's and nice conceited Ladies, which I thought had been an Invention of our times. You approve not then, ſaid the Chevalier, that the Princeſs ſhould be ſo difficult of acceſs, or that ſo much Wit ſhould be neceſſary to be imployed in gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her favour; but for all that, I fancy that you have leaſt reaſon of any perſon in the World to diſlike it: for I believe it would be to your advantage, if there were ſuch nice Genius in all Courts where you come: methinks for that only reaſon you ſhould love them; for when things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98279:8"/>
or done with an ill grace, do you not think that a little diſdain or averſion ſhewed, becomes a Lady very well, ſo as it be but juſt enough to give one cauſe to gueſs that it is ſo?</p>
               <p>I am of your Judgment, ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal, but there is a kind of an affected deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, which cannot allow of any thing which one is not accuſtomed to ſee, and deſpiſes rigorouſly every thing that is not greater or no longer in the Mode, which ſeems to me to proceed from a dark under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding or want of wit.</p>
               <p>But to return to our nice Queen, was it not unreaſonable in her to expect, that a man who is bred to Arms, ſhould ſhew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Profeſſion, but when he faces the Enemy? How is it poſſible that any one can ſpend his life in the Wars, and not ſmell a little of the Souldier? The Wars, ſaid the Chevalier, we muſt grant to be the fineſt imployment in the World; but to take it right, a well bred man hath no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion at all: For though he underſtands a thing perfectly well, and is in a manner obliged to paſs his life in it, it ſeems to me, that neither his Actions nor his Converſe ſhould ſhew any signs of it, he takes too deep
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98279:9"/>
a tincture of nothing, and his Wit and good Senſe teaches him how to behave himſelf on all occaſions. What a fine Idæa you give me, cryed the Mareſhal, I am much pleaſed with fancying to my ſelf our young <hi>Prince</hi> to be of this kind of Wit: we cannot take a more noble Subject to entertain our ſelves withal, and you know that very few days paſs wherein I ſpeak not ſomething of him. I remember very well where we left when we were interrupted. I was aſking, whether you were not of that opinion, that it would do well for him to learn the Language of the ancient <hi>Romans,</hi> which is ſpoken by ſo many good men and ſuch a number of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors. It is not only to be valued as good in it ſelf (anſwered the Chevalier) but there is very much advantage to be made by underſtanding it; we find in it ſo many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things, and that in their Original: for you muſt needs confeſs, that when any one ſpeaks, there is ſomething ſo clear and natural, which proceeds from the Wit and Underſtanding of the perſon expreſſed in apt and ſignificant words, which cannot by all the Art imaginable be rendred into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Language, as to be altogether the ſame. I find alſo that the Art which is uſed to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98279:9"/>
teach that Tongue, gives a great light into all the other Languages, and that we may by knowing it, ſpeak our own the better and with more aſſurance. Beſides, being at this day the moſt known and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, the Prince would be glad (eſpecially if he ſhould one day become the Arbiter of the World) to underſtand what ſo many Nations ſhould ſay to him, and to expreſs himſelf without an Interpreter.</p>
               <p>Is it an eaſie matter (ſaid the Mareſhal) to learn it in a little time? The more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary part of any Language (anſwered the Chevalier) will aſk but little time; and yet it is of great benefit when one knows it. But the Niceties which depend much on the ſkill of the Teacher, and on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons we hear ſpeak, are more difficult. You know, in all other things, what it is to give the laſt touch. I ſhould be of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (continued the Chevalier) that now in his Youth it would be beſt to divide and ſet apart his hours, for fear of oppreſſing him too much, and giving him a diſguſt of what he ſhould learn: and make him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to practiſe ſuch little Exerciſes for the activity of his body, as his age and ſtrength permits, he would be the better ſhap't and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98279:10"/>
more healthful: that it will be good like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to divertize his Studies and his Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations too, as ſhould be thought moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient: and I believe his hours ſhould not be too regular; for even pleaſure it ſelf, if it be offered always in ſo orderly a way, and at ſet times, becomes tireſom and looks like conſtraint.</p>
               <p>I fancy now in his tender age (in which they may make what impreſſions they pleaſe, but not ſo eaſily blot out again hereafter) they ſhould order it ſo, that thoſe who come about him, ſhould be of thoſe perſons who are lucky in all things, and whoſe demeanour and preſence may not accuſtom him to any thing which is fit for him to forget. I would have the like re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard had in chuſing thoſe Maſters who come to teach him the ſmalleſt things. I know there will not want thoſe who will ſay, that this is but a fancy; but I am very certain, that as for all ſorts of Exerciſes, as well thoſe of the body as of the mind, it were to be wiſhed, that ſuch as are moſt ſkilful and able to perform them beſt, might form in him that unexpreſſible gracefulneſs, which moſt Maſters want themſelves: and alſo that after ſome time, <hi>Monſieur de</hi> D. T.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98279:10"/>
and likewiſe <hi>Monſieur le</hi> P. might diſcourſe to him of the Wars, and ſhew what ways Conquerours took to be great. For I am perſwaded, that of what Birth ſoever any one is, he may think himſelf much honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have contributed any thing to a work of ſo great conſequence, and that all thoſe things which a young Prince ought to learn, cannot come from a perſon of two good a Family.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, that <hi>Cæſar</hi> by combating and running through all parts, from <hi>Europe</hi> into <hi>Aſia,</hi> and thence into <hi>Africa,</hi> loſt moſt part of his old Souldiers; and that he himſelf inſtructed new-raiſed men to hold the Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and uſe the Sword, or the Javelin; Do you not think that by learning of ſuch a Maſter, the inſtruction took much deeper impreſſion, and ſpread it ſelf further, even without being aware of it?</p>
               <p>What is ſaid of handſom perſons (anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Mareſhal) that every thing becomes them, may be ſaid with more reaſon of dexterous and judicious perſons. I ſhould have been glad to have ſeen that Maſters of the World play the Fencing-maſter. Whatſoever I had obſerved from ſo great a man, would have taught me ſomething
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98279:11"/>
that I ſhould have been glad to remember. And that which you ſaid juſt now is very true, That there are ſome perſons whoſe Company we cannot too much frequent. 'Tis certain, that by ſeeing them often, on whatſoever occaſion it may be, beſides the improvement that we have by being with them, we gain a good eſteem to our ſelves; as we perfume our ſelves, unawares by walking amongſt the Jaſmins and Orange-Trees.</p>
               <p>There cannot any thing be imagined more gallant, and truly, ſaid the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, you have a great exactneſs in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. I know very well, ſaid the Mareſhal, when I am minded to be pleaſant: and I thought it would ſurprize you. If you did ſurprize me, ſaid the Chevalier, 'twas the better to pleaſe me. A thing that is well conceived, ought likewiſe to be well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and I think there is nothing more pleaſant.</p>
               <p>For all that, anſwered the Mareſhal, I am the man in the World that leaſt ſtudies thoſe kind of florid expreſſions. Neither do I much affect exactneſs in ſpeaking. To be punctual and juſt, as to the ſenſe I love always; but to be ſo in words, appears
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98279:11"/>
commonly too much affected: and if I did deſire to be eloquent, I ſhould wiſh to be ſo with my heart and underſtanding. No man wants words when he has any thing to ſay to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>People talk as long as they pleaſe (ſaid the Chevalier) of what relates to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of the World: we find but too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that are ſkilled in that way of diſcourſe: but for ſome other things which are leſs clear, and not eaſie to be conceived, one is many times puzled to expreſs them, as one has a mind to do. 'Tis true, that a perſon may be ſaid to be eloquent, who firſt had the conception of them, in what manner ſoever he makes others underſtand them. Thoſe who think well are never too long nor tedious, for they ſeek words only to expreſs their thoughts; whereas others ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more how to ſpeak finely, than how to expreſs themſelves.</p>
               <p>As to exactneſs in ſpeaking, I find two ſorts which have always good effects: the one conſiſts in diſcerning things as they are, and without confounding them: for if we fail never ſo little, either in ſpeaking or acting, it is preſently perceived and taken notice of: this depends upon the Wit and Underſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98279:12"/>
The other, juſtneſs or exactneſs of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing appears in being able to judge of the decency of our expreſſions, and in having true meaſures how far we ought to go, and when to ſtop. This which proceeds chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the reliſh and judgment we have of things, ſeems to me more doubtful and difficult.</p>
               <p>The exactneſs of words pleaſes when it is without affectation, and words are not played and gingled withal. But I can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that one cannot have too much of that kind of juſtneſs of Speech, which conſiſts in the knowing how to make uſe of the apteſt and moſt proper words and the beſt forms of ſpeaking, to infuſe our thoughts into the minds of others in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we deſire; neither more nor leſs.</p>
               <p>Theſe exactneſſes are always approved of, provided we be not too ſevere and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous in expecting them from others; and that we remember that <hi>Roman</hi> Lady, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom one might not ſo much as trip; for as ſhe was one day preſſing and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon an excellent man, who was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing intangled and out of order, he told her; ſhe was in the right, but that ſhe was a little to blame to take away the pleaſure of freedom and negligence.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98279:12"/>
We are much more civil to Ladies now a-days, ſaid the Mareſhal, than they were in thoſe times: and whatever they ſay now does not diſcompoſe any body that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the World. They may venture at any thing, eſpecially when they are hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom. But an accompliſht perſon, though of never ſo much merit, ought not to be too confident of himſelf: yea, the more he excels others, the more care he ought to take not to preſcribe to the Company, but to be complying. For naturally every one is afraid of a Maſter-wit.</p>
               <p>I love thoſe perſons who always ſhew ſome Wit without offending any one, and I perfectly hate thoſe who make uſe of it only to the diſpleaſing of others. It is good to avoid the converſe of ſuch, as much as one can: for this humour proceeds from the pride and maliciouſneſs of their nature, which mingles it ſelf in all their actions, There are others of them, who are more raſh than malicious, who, to vent a Jeſt, will make ſport with, and play upon every body, without conſidering the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. What advantage is it to have Wit, if one cannot make uſe of it for the gaining of the good opinion and love of the World?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98279:13"/>
One may withdraw and abſent ones ſelf, if things go not to ones mind: but when we come into Company, we ſhould carry our ſelves ſo, that we may be acceptable to thoſe perſons with whom we are, although we have no great kindneſs for them. For thoſe who think to revenge themſelves by a croſs Carriage, do to themſelves more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury than they do to others.</p>
               <p>I know ſome alſo who are froward and diſagreeable, out of a principle of envy. This is a fault which diſguſts me moſt of all, which diſcovers a mean Spirit and a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Wit. For if one well underſtood what Life and Fortune is, it would incline one rather to pity, than envy thoſe whom the World thinks happy. I have ſeen ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure perſons and of very ordinary capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who would equal themſelves with the chief men of the World, and who by no means would conſent to, nor allow of their reputations.</p>
               <p>There are others who would gladly pleaſe and gain love: but neither honour, truth, nor the benefit of thoſe who hear them, can make them ſay any thing, unleſs it tends directly to their own proper ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. 'Tis an ill way they take; for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98279:13"/>
the World thinks not well of thoſe who are only for themſelves, but it always approves of thoſe who endeavour to advance the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations of thoſe that deſerve it. Sir (ſaid the Chevalier) your Art is marvellous: For the thing that was in queſtion, was only concerning the exactneſs of Language, or ſomething like it, yet by degrees, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt inſenſibly, you are fallen upon the diſcourſe of the Commerce of the World, and you have deſcribed thoſe perſons who make ill uſe of their Wit; and who only ſpeak for their own intereſt: which ſhews that you have obſerved the Court, and that you are not well pleaſed with the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Manners of it.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only add to that which you ſaid juſt now, That when any one ſpeaks, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever deſign he may have, that of pleaſing ſhould always be one: but that ought not to be the ſole or principal end. Nature tends only to things neceſſary. There is nothing in the faireſt body of the World which is not neceſſary for life or motion. Good chear is founded upon the neceſſity of eating and drinking. Lodging muſt be had, and that is the cauſe we love fine hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; for at firſt we only ſeek thoſe things
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98279:14"/>
we cannot want: and afterwards we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, and deſire the pleaſure into the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain (if we may be allowed to ſpeak ſo) as an accidental thing which rejoyces us, though we did not expect it.</p>
               <p>I allow (ſaid the Mareſhal) that a man take the liberty to expreſs himſelf, let it be in what way he pleaſes: and I underſtand you very well. I believe the beſt way to improve ones ſelf and become knowing, is not to ſtudy over-much, but to entertain our ſelves often, and diſcourſe of thoſe things that open the Underſtanding. And it would be good (if I miſtake not) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom our young Prince to this, and to place people about him who might inſtruct him in that manner. As for ſuch Ladies as are placed about him, I do not ſee that there need be ſuch care in the choice of them. I confeſs, I ſhould only have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to thoſe of the pleaſanteſt humour, to keep him always chearful. For excepting a very few, (the wiſeſt of them appear to me to have little ſenſe) though otherwiſe they may pleaſe. You judge well, that from ſome certain agreeableneſs in the face or ſhape, we can conclude nothing concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Underſtanding. And thoſe who
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98279:14"/>
are able to diſcern one from the other, are ſeldom deceived.</p>
               <p>The World will not allow Women to be wiſe, ſaid the Chevalier, but I know not why, unleſs it be perhaps, becauſe they are commended enough for other qualities, and that they are handſom. For the World delights to leſſen on one ſide what it is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to allow on the other. And if it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny a man to be very brave, it will never agree that he is other ways well bred, although in reality he excels moſt in the latter. In my opinion it is not ſo rare a thing to meet with Ladies of good Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. I find in them a delicacy of Wit which is not ſo common to men; and I have likewiſe obſerved in many places and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all ſorts of Qualities, that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mens actions are not attended with ſo much gracefulneſs as Womens are; and that Ladies are more ſkilful than they in what they do: whether it be that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of pleaſing be more natural to them, or that they finding their greateſt ſtrength to lie there, they make it more their ſtudy from their Childhood. Two or three of them, (if I am not miſtaken) have begun to undeceive the Court concerning
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98279:15"/>
your falſe Gallantry, and if we thought there were no glory nor pleaſure in gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their favours, we ſhould not ſtudy ſo many ways to render our ſelves agreeable to them. Beſides, no perſon is ever well bred, or at leaſt a perfect gallant man, in whoſe making the Ladies have not had a hand.</p>
               <p>How much am I obliged to you (ſaid the Mareſhal) for making a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the well bred man and the gallant man? We are apt to miſtake and confound one with the other. It ſeems to me (ſaid the Chevalier) that the excellence of a Gallant conſiſts in the common way of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; and we find in him a certain plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of Carriage, which a well bred man always hath not. But a well bred man hath more ſolid vertues, though he be leſs buſie and forward to ſhew himſelf in the World.</p>
               <p>There's a great deal of difference betwixt the one and the other (ſaid the Mareſhal) This quality of a Gallant, which pleaſes in young people, paſſes away like a flower or a dream; and I have ſeen ſome of theſe gallant men become the neglect and ſcorn even of thoſe who once admired them. But if we love a man for his good breeding and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98279:15"/>
honeſty, we always love him, and 'tis not in the power of time to make it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>I imagine, ſaid the Chevalier, that when thoſe gallant men were ſo much eſteemed of, yet all the World was not ſo dazled with them: and that there were always ſome who ſeigned that it was but a falſe Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and a glittering Varniſh, which might perhaps ſurprize. But true Gallantry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt perſons who underſtand it, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways well received. It depends but very little upon the advantages of the body: nay, it happens many times, that a deformed man hath a better grace than another, who ſeems made on purpoſe to be made for a Picture. It is not enough to have a fine outſide to make one agreeable; that which is of greateſt importance is the well regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our Intellectuals, and the taking are that our head and heart be in good order<hi>:</hi> for one can never be a gallant man without having a good heart and much wit.</p>
               <p>This true Gallantry appears principally in the knowing how to ſet a pleaſing gloſs upon things that are in themſelves diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. For many times that which diſguſts us moſt, we ſhould the better endure, if a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98279:16"/>
good colour were put upon it; and if we conſidered it ſo as to make the beſt of it. I remember there were two friends that went to viſit a Lady, and he that was the worſt received by her, imagined, that to gain her favour, there was nothing wanting but to ruine his friend in her opinion. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who perceived it, inſtead of complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or being enraged at it; I knew very well (ſaid he to him) that you had a love for me, but I did not believe that you thought me deſerving enough to be in the favour of a Lady of ſuch merit, and who is ſo good a Judge of men: theſe thoughts of yours are ſo advantagious to me, that they cannot any ways be an occaſion of the breach of our friendſhip.</p>
               <p>This (ſaid the Mareſhal) ſeems to me perfectly gallant, I know not whether ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that hath been told me of a great Princeſs, proceeded not from a Wit of the ſame nature. She was informed, that a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worthy well bred man (but a little fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtical) found ſome fault with her Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: we have (ſaid ſhe) but two many Flatterers; that which you tell me of this Gentleman, is rather an advice than a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; 'tis none of his fault that I am not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98279:16"/>
better; and I am much obliged to him for it.</p>
               <p>There could not any thing have been found out more juſt (ſaid the Chevalier) and it makes me my ſelf better underſtand my own thoughts. This Princeſs muſt, without doubt, have been more than an ordinary perſon. Oh! how happy ſhould we be, if all things that paſs in the World were conſtrued after this manner. I fancy (continued the Chevalier) that a gallant man is no other than a well bred honeſt man, only a little more briſk and ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling than ordinary, and who has the Art to make every thing become him; however there is a great advantage to be made by knowing how to be both the one and the other, as we ſee occaſion. And I have ſeen ſome worthy good men, who have been much to ſeek amongſt Ladies, how to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate themſelves into their Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though they have had very rational things to ſay to them.</p>
               <p>Rational? (cryed the Mareſhal) who could ever have it in their heads to uſe their reaſon ſo unſeaſonably? The Ladies are neither ſo coy nor ſo ſevere as to ſtand upon reaſon on ſuch occaſions; but they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98279:17"/>
would be accoſted gallantly and boldly, as you know they would have neat addreſſes, an airy and frolick Converſation, an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able compliſance, with a little flattery, and that <hi>je ne ſcay quoy</hi> of ſmartneſs and wit to ſtir and warn them without perplexing them<hi>:</hi> that way which is now uſed in the moſt refined and civilized parts of the World which takes with every body. A confident yet a modeſt Carriage, which is neither mean nor ſullen, having nothing which ſavours not of goodneſs and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</p>
               <p>He that knows how to perform his Courtſhip after this manner, may in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion become of great conſideration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Ladies; and that is the ſureſt way to pleaſe them<hi>:</hi> but it is alſo the moſt hazardous, unleſs it be carried very ſkill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and with a good grace. For we muſt remember, that the more ſuch kind of things are agreeable when they are well done, the more they diſpleaſe when they are ill performed.</p>
               <p>It may beſides be added, ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, that few people are born with theſe perfections, nor ſkilled in the managing of ſo glorious a courſe of life, and if it ſhould
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98279:17"/>
be ones fortune to ſucceed in perfection, the moſt part of Women are not much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with it: at leaſt 'tis certain, that ſo much ſmartneſs and frowardneſs will at length tire them.</p>
               <p>I find that thoſe Women who have the moſt wit, like much better a little more reſervedneſs: and commonly thoſe people are unfortunately diſappointed of their aims, that do not know that they are gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame ways that we are gained; and likewiſe loſt after the ſame manner. They throw as it were their hearts at their heads, and at firſt daſh tell them more of their Love than can in any probability be true, and many times more than they deſire to hear. They give them not time ſo much as to wiſh that they were loved, and to taſte of a certain ſweetneſs which is only found in the progreſs of Love. That pleaſure muſt be long enjoyed to make Love laſt for ever: there is but little plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in obtaining that which we have not very much deſired; and when we have it ſo eaſily, we accuſtom our ſelves to neglect it, and commonly come there no more. But troubel not your ſelf about Ladies for our young Prince, there will enough offer
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98279:18"/>
themſelves when the time comes.</p>
               <p>As they were ſpeaking, one came to tell them, that there was ſomething in diſpute amongſt the Ladies, who were, as I told you, at play in another Room, and they deſired them to come and give their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. It could not have happened more opportunely, ſaid the Mareſhal, juſt when we were ſo ſeaſonably upon the Theme of Ladies. For if we would not diſpleaſe any of them, we had need to ſummon all our wits to judge between them. Let us do the Houſe right, and we will conclude for this day. To morrow I will expect you, and give order that we may not be diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:98279:18"/>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>THE SECOND CONVERSATION.</head>
               <p>THoſe who are at the Court make more Friends and Acquaintance, than thoſe who live retired. But of that number of Friends, few of them are really ſo, and for the moſt part they are as little underſtood by any of the Court, as they themſelves perfectly underſtand the Court. Not that it is ſo, as 'tis generally ſaid, That Courtiers love nothing, and that they ſtudy their own intereſt more than how to diſcern and eſteem true me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. For peoples hearts and minds are much the ſame there as in other places, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt ſways through all the World. But in that place we are divided amongſt ſo many people, that every one has but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of us, and that ſuperficially, according as every one deſires; and commonly we fix not upon any one, either to love, or perfectly to underſtand.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98279:19"/>
The Chevalier who had ſeen the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal ſo much abroad in the World, and who knew well enough that he was a very gallant man, yet had not ſo great an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of him then when he ſeldom ſaw him, as now, and having frequented him ſeven or eight days in retirement, he knew not how to be abſent from him.</p>
               <p>He therefore failed not to come the next day, as they had appointed: and being with him betimes, he engaged him to paſs the morning at play, and before they left off, he ordered it ſo, that they ſhould be obliged to ſet to it again after dinner; though it was a great delight to him to hear him diſcourſe, yet he always found ſome invention or other to hinder him from ſpeaking much. For the Mareſhal, to whom any great agitation was hurtful, was eaſily moved (and contrary to the cuſtom of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſons that are much in the World, and who dive but little into things) is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively thoughtful, and ſpeaks often with much eagerneſs, and with as much action as if he were in perfect health. They plaid only to paſs the time as one ought always with true friends; for if high play deſtroy not friendſhip, yet it may leſſen it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98279:19"/>
After they had played a long time, the Mareſhal ſpake of going into a Meadow by the ſide of a little River which runneth at the foot of the Town: but the heat of the day being not yet paſt, he began to walk in the Chamber, and told the Chevalier he was thinking of that Queen of <hi>Egypt.</hi> As I was riſing this morning, ſaid he, I was laughing at that man that you repreſented to me, I fancied that I ſaw him with her, entertaining her with ſuch fine things, as martial men uſe to ſay to Ladies.</p>
               <p>That which pleaſed you, ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, was, that you have no cauſe to fear if you ſhould meet with any perſons that are ſo nice and delicate. Not too much of that (ſaid the Mareſhal) for I ſhould be apt enough to ſhew ſomething of my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, if I had not a care. And ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have done me the favour to give me an <hi>Item</hi> of it; and to ſay the truth. I have but little Learning, and you cannot imagine how I am vexed at it; but I hope my Children will be more knowing than their Maſters themſelves.</p>
               <p>Do not regret ſo much, ſaid the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, that having ſtudied ſo little, you have only loſt a little Latine by it, which they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98279:20"/>
would have taught you. That is very much (replied the Mareſhal) if there were nothing elſe: but beſides, would they not have inſtructed me in thoſe Sciences which my Friend <hi>X.</hi> eſteems ſo much.</p>
               <p>As he was enlarging himſelf upon the diſcourſe, which he had had with that Friend; You ſpeak not like a man without Learning (ſaid the Chevalier) that which I have now heard from you, would make you be admired: and in truth, you know very much for a Souldier and a great Courtier.</p>
               <p>The Mareſhal began to laugh, and told him, that he knew nothing of the Science but their names. The Maſters themſelves, replied the Chevalier, know but very little more. They would have taught you all that which they ordinarily teach others with much expence of time and great pains, and you ſhould not have underſtood the more, nor been more learned, unleſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by that means you might have been undeceived as to the value you ſet upon them.</p>
               <p>What you ſay (anſwered the Mareſhal after a little conſideration) in probabilty may be true; and you make me call to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98279:20"/>
mind how I have ſpent whole days with this man to hear him diſcourſe of the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. I confeſs freely to you, that it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways happened that I could not apprehend him; the more he took pains to explain himſelf, the leſs he made himſelf under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. For to judge of Philoſophy by the Idæa that he gave me of it, I repreſented it to my ſelf like the night, and I aſked him, whether it were eſſential to it to be dark and obſcure.</p>
               <p>This (ſaid he) is a very fair beginning, I have known thoſe who have been longer at it, who could not have ſaid ſo much. But to diſguiſe nothing to you, all this is never well underſtood but when it is lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in our Youth.</p>
               <p>One underſtands it not the better (ſaid the Chevalier) for being exerciſed in it in our youth, but we are leſs ſurpriſed with the obſcurity of it. Theſe people are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed from their youth to ſpeak of all things without diſcerning any thing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly. That which they ſay never ſeems obſcure nor confuſed to them, and the moſt part of them imagine, that they are very well underſtood, although it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to know their meanings.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98279:21"/>
How comes it to paſs then (ſaid the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal) that we profit not by thoſe Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the Ancients have left us, and ſo many other great men ſince that time? I would tell you what I think of it, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Chevalier, if I were not afraid to tire you, for the Subject hath but little of divertiſement in it. Beſides, it ſeems to me, that people ſhould do well to practiſe what they already know, without endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring either to eſtabliſh it, or teach it to others: And I for my part who knows ſo little, have no reaſon to meddle in the matter.</p>
               <p>I reſted well laſt night (ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal) and we have dined ſo well, that for this day all Subjects will be acceptable to me, and I defie you to weary me. Beſides, there is nothing ſo dull, but may be made pleaſant by the help of a good Wit, and I find that you have to ſpare.</p>
               <p>Sir (ſaid the Chevalier) you love to be merry. I ſpeak of you (replied the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal) as I ſhould ſpeak to you of my ſelf. I endeavour to ſhew neither vanity nor flattery; and I find the beſt men have but little of either, yet a little flattery may be uſed on ſome occaſions, if it be done diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98279:21"/>
but vanity is always ill becoming: and I ſee beſides, that commonly that which vain perſons have moſt commendable in them is deſpiſed. It is good to hide it, but much better to quit ones ſelf quite of it if one can. For if one takes never ſo much care not to let it appear, there comes from it inſenſibly I know not what which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth. This defect, which I fear ſo much, hinders me not from telling you, that though the Intrigues of the World and ſome kind of Ambition have permitted me to be but little ſpeculative; yet I love ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely to meet a certain ſprightlineſs and vivacity diffuſing it ſelf every way with a comlineſs and grace.</p>
               <p>I have been thought to have had ſome ſparks of it; however there is nothing of all that which people love and admire, which affects me to that point. I muſt open the bottom of my heart to you, I have but little reaſon to be fond of life, and I know how I ought to conſider the World; but how much ſoever we are diſ-engaged, thoſe who have Children cannot out look often upon them with a concern. I have ſome very hopeful, and I am perſwaded, that which we now diſcourſe on, may one day
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98279:22"/>
be uſeful to them. And that is it which obligeth me to ſpeak upon ſo many Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. But to return to that which I aſked you; how comes it to paſs, that we draw ſo little advantage from the Learning which thoſe able <hi>Græcians</hi> have left us?</p>
               <p>You have often ſpoken to me of <hi>Greece,</hi> and the ſmalleſt matters that you told me of it, have much delighted me.</p>
               <p>I ſhould be glad that you would now again conduct me through theſe renowned places, and that by the way you could make me obſerve that which you think moſt conſiderable in them.</p>
               <p>When he had ſaid this, he took a ſeat, and cauſed the Chevalier to ſit down, who began in this manner.</p>
               <p>Since you will have it ſo, I muſt tell you, that <hi>Greece</hi> was the moſt pleaſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode that can be imagined. The Air of the Country is mild and ſerene, and ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, that it ſeldom happens that either Winter or Summer is troubleſom to them. There was abundance of all things that can be deſired to live happily. The men there were born very dextrous at all ſorts of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, and Art eaſily compleats that which Nature hath ſo well begun. The Ladies
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98279:22"/>
of <hi>Athens</hi> were naturally very courtly, and rather brown than fair. There was a kind of ſharpneſs in their Converſation which pleaſed. And as there often appears in a dark and ſtill night ſome flaſhes of light, ſo although their manner of ſpeaking was plain and reſerved, there brake forth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways a great deal of wit. 'Twas ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that the ſound of their voices was ſo harmonious and charming, that the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that alone was ſufficient to delight. But beſides the pureneſs and delicacy of this Language, how many fine things do you think was ſaid in it. For there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who were not contented with the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and addreſs of the body only, but ſought after other accompliſhments. No people in the World were more apt to love, nor knew how to make love better.</p>
               <p>This Country had the proper Genius to invent Arts, and to bring them to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Painting appeared there in its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence, full of ſpirit and paſſion. There was in it always ſome invention which ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed and pleaſed much more. What has not been ſaid of the Sacrifice of <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> which could not be looked on without tears? And of that Tablet of <hi>Roxana</hi> and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98279:23"/>
                  <hi>Alexander,</hi> where the little <hi>Cupids</hi> put Chains of Mirtles and Roſes about this great Conquerour, to lead him to the feet of his Priſoner? So ſtrange an adventure might at firſt hold us in admiration; but this Captive appeared with ſo ſurpriſing a Beauty, that when they conſidered her a little, they no longer wondred at her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</p>
               <p>There are alſo at this day ſome of their Statues to be ſeen, which would make one fancy there were ſomething more than hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane in them. This reaſon alone, if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, methinks might excuſe the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of theſe times for having adored them.</p>
               <p>They were ſo ſkillful in Muſick, that by adding and varying certain Notes, they knew how to affect the heart as they had a mind. Did you never hear how <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in the midſt of a Feaſt, when there was nothing thought of but Mirth and Jolity, was ſo charmed and tranſported with thoſe Sounds, that he ran to his Arms, as if he had ſeen the Enemy? For it was a ſort of violence and enchantment, the ſecret of which is not come to us, or at leaſt that in it, which was moſt rare is loſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98279:23"/>
Their Eloquence needs not to be ſpoke of, it ſpeaks enough it ſelf: and who can ſo well expreſs what it was as it ſelf? And did not all thoſe fine Verſes, which appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their making, make the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that it was the Language of the Gods, and that they ſpoke it in <hi>Greece</hi> as it was ſpoken in Heaven? To conclude all, thoſe excellent Knowledges which have ſpread into all parts, have come from that happy Country, and even the <hi>Romans,</hi> who ſince that have made ſo much noiſe, have not excelled in ſo many things but by their imitating the <hi>Grecians,</hi> who were the firſt Inventors.</p>
               <p>As they were a people of great reaſon, ſo it was their nature to live peaceably; but however they were very Martial. There were always of them Souldiers and Generals, who knew both how to fight and command. This <hi>Alexander</hi> who was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed according to the Diſcipline of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> with a little money and but a few men, had the Courage to go and attacque the richeſt and greateſt Monarch of the Earth, and to overcome him twice in ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Battel in the midſt of five or ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:98279:24"/>
This young Conquerour, who ran through all parts in ſearch of Glory, had a Preceptor who thought it no leſs in his way; and if the Scholar rendred himſelf Maſter of the World, we may ſay alſo, that the Preceptor as well by his own ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as by the favour of this Prince, had the Empire in Sciences. He had ſuch a Wit as is requiſite to make him able in that which concerned living in the World; but as to certain knowledges more hidden, he went not ſo far as ſome others who had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded him.</p>
               <p>Thoſe made it their felicity to know, and ſaid, that they knew almoſt nothing: they were honeſt men, and of a ſincere faith, and treated doubtfully of doubtful things: and for ſuch things as they could compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend clearly, although they were of the higheſt ſpeculation, they diſcourſed of them nevertheleſs in ſuch a manner, as ſavoured neither of Art nor Study; but ſo clearly and naturally, that there needed only a good Wit to underſtand them at the very firſt.</p>
               <p>This perſon who made it not ſo much his aim to be learned, as to gain the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of being ſo, found very well they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98279:24"/>
were above him, and that thoſe who were good Judges of Wit and Learning, would never put him in the firſt rank. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſwaded that a ſmall number (that nothing could dazle nor delude) who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to what degree things were valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, would not be favourable to him, he applied himſelf to gain thoſe who were not ſo clear-ſighted, and to make himſelf admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the multitude.</p>
               <p>To effect this, knowing well what ſort of people he had to deal with, and what would beſt take with them, he reſolved to be poſitive, and to decide like a Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and to inſinuate to them, that they needed but only to underſtand him to be learned. He borrowed the inventions of thoſe who were little known, which he uſed as his own, and turned all the reſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>ridicule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some ſaid, that the foundations of his Building are not very ſure, and that he eſtabliſhed Principles, which are not only obſcure and doubtful, but beſides ſo falſe and improbable, that a very ordinary ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity may diſcover the abuſe. However, I could wiſh that a man of ſuch Eminency had a little more naturalized the Art and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98279:25"/>
the Rules; for it ſeems to me, that the ſmalleſt matters which the meaneſt capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties comprehend when they are naturally and plainly ſpoken, will puzzle the moſt able, when delivered in an intricate me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and a ſtudied way, which appears in all the Writings we ſee of his.</p>
               <p>That which he ſaid well, and was well underſtood, might perhaps be the cauſe of bringing an eſteem upon all the reſt which was not underſtood. For he hath written many very good things; and that which ſeems ſtrange to me is, that people neglect them, becauſe they underſtand them: they are of a belief, that there is nothing good which is not obſcure, ſo that they are ſo far from following the light of Reaſon, and framing themſelves according to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of this learned <hi>Greece,</hi> that they ſeek nothing but falſe Subtilties and Chimerical diſtinctions. The Maſter teacheth a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which he himſelf underſtands not, and which he had from another that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it as little. Hence it comes, that a young man after ten or twelve years ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy knows nothing; and that thoſe who have applied themſelves all their life time to this Doctrine, are but the more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98279:25"/>
They are ſo much out of the way, that every one ſcorns to talk any more to them about it. For the but natural Wits are apt to take an ill habit by it; and being once accuſtomed to conſider things in that manner, they never after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards conſider them as they really are. I have likewiſe obſerved, that when any of this order of men are ſpoke of as truly learned, able men, 'tis commonly a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake; there is a mixture in them of Art and Fallacy together, which is very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtful.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Euclide</hi> and <hi>Archimedes,</hi> of whom we have formerly diſcourſed, thoſe who endeavour to perfect themſelves in their Science, always make ſome progreſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: that which it teacheth is indubitable, and would to God we could learn with the ſame certainty all other things that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know. 'Tis good to ſeaſon a mans mind with this Science, becauſe it makes one accurate and judicious; but 'tis not good to engage ones ſelf too far therein, in regard it withdraws people from the Converſe of the World, and renders them too ſpeculative. And to meet with that which we look for in it, and likewiſe to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98279:26"/>
make others comprehend it, we muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by long reaſonings and inductions, from line to line, and from figure to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; and when we have found it, we for the moſt part find too, that we might as well have been without it. Beſides, that this method is not only tedious, and that it hath never been the Language of any Court in the World; it ſeems to me, that when we ſay any thing that is handſom, high, or of conſequence, it always carries its own light with it to make it underſtood, in caſe it be well expreſſed.</p>
               <p>The Chevalier making a pauſe, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal who had hearkned to him very atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, aſked him whether that regular Maſter who marched always in order at the head of the Doctors, had taught thoſe dark and dull Sciences to that young airy Prince? There are Sciences which ſeem more curious than neceſſary (anſwered the Chevalier) and I do not believe, that that perſon who underſtood ſo well what it is that ſets the excellent Princes above the ordinary ones, had much burdened him with it; he had a mind to make a Heroe of this young Prince, which in truth he did, and formed him by <hi>Homers</hi> pattern.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98279:26"/>
It is true, that when he inſtructed him in thoſe things that were of the moſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he was not wanting to diſcover to him the greateſt ſecrets of his knowledge. That which makes me ſpeak, it is becauſe he publiſhed ſome Books of this nature, and <hi>Alexander</hi> writ him a Letter, wherein he ſhewed enough his diſlike of it.</p>
               <p>Is this Letter (ſaid the Mareſhal) come down to us? I ſhould be glad to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Prince had the ſame Genius in theſe matters which made him ſo admired in others; and whether great men ſhew their greatneſs in their meaneſt actions. You may judge of the Letter (ſaid the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier) for it being not long, I remember it, and this is it word for word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ought not to have made publick ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent things which I had from you, how ſhall I for the future appear to have any advantage or knowledge above other men, if they know the ſame things which you have taught me? You did not conſider, that I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved rather to ſurpaſs others in knowledge and wit, than in all things which relate to Power and Grandeur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the Letter, and are you not amazed, that <hi>Alexander</hi> ſhould write it in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98279:27"/>
the middle of his Glory and in the ſtrength of his Ambition? Muſt he not needs have a very vaſt mind and a wit of great extent, to be concerned for ſuch things as theſe, which Conquerours commonly make little account of?</p>
               <p>What a man was this! (ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal) he aimed to be the firſt in every thing; and who, after all this, can think that it was Fortune alone that rendred him ſo puiſſant, and that merit had the greateſt part therein?</p>
               <p>But to return to the Sciences; I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend very well, that this able Preceptor applied himſelf to that which was moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. It ſeems to me, that in order to become a great Prince, and to govern the World, a man cannot know too many things.</p>
               <p>I agree with you (ſaid the Chevalier) but there is an extreme difference in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtructed, as an Artiſt who would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in his Trade; and in Learning how to diſcourſe and underſtand the reaſon of any Subject which is offered, without any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſign than to learn what it is, and not to be miſtaken. This laſt knowledge, though it be very ornamental and of great
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98279:27"/>
uſe; yet it coſts but little pains, when we meet with ſuch perſons as go directly to the point.</p>
               <p>That which I would principally wiſh in a King is, that he ſhould have wit and be a juſt man, and every way accompliſhed: and in my judgment he cannot be too per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in either of theſe Qualities. Beſides, 'tis true, how happy ſoever we are, or whatſoever new advantages we may have either of body or mind, we ſhould ſtrive to be able and ſkillful in affairs, and begin there, if we can; for without that the reſt ſucceeds not always well, and it oftentimes happens, that for want of ſkill, that which is beſt in us turns to our ruine. But it is not good to diſcover too much of this craſt and fore-ſight; for the generality of the World affect not naturally thoſe that have ſo much of caution and prudence, but are rather moſt favourable to thoſe who put themſelves upon adventures, and expoſe all to hazard. Hence it comes, that ſo many perſons (eſpecially the Ladies) like not <hi>Cæſar</hi> ſo well as <hi>Alexander.</hi> This Talent of being able conſiſts in a certain dexterity and particular Genius, and is converſant in making a right uſe of that which is in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98279:28"/>
our power and of that which we know; but if we are ignorant, and have nothing in our power, ſuch a kind of Genius will but little avail us. Therefore to have where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to imploy it, we muſt get our ſelves a Repute, and be well informed of things how they may be of uſe to us. Thoſe who have this kind of wit love to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves valued, and to take their advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; but they take no great pains to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat themſelves in any thing. Beſides, the affairs of the World hinder them from fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on any particular thing; nor do you find that the ableſt excel in all things.</p>
               <p>I ſhould be of an opinion (ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal) that a Prince ſhould addict himſelf to Hiſtory; for it diſcovers ſo many things, that one may by it render himſelf able and knowing, at leaſt it is a good guide as to what concerns life. 'Tis true (ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier) Hiſtory may be of great uſe, were it only to perſwade by Examples that which we have a mind to, when we have but weak reaſons to give for it, or that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make good ones be hearkned to. But the events being different (although the Conjunctures are alike) it is difficult to eſtabliſh any thing certainly upon it, and I
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98279:28"/>
believe that one may be able and knowing without the help of Hiſtory. When there was neither track nor mark of it, did not our Fore-fathers underſtand the good and the evil?</p>
               <p>Beſides, all things poſſible that we can imagine to our ſelves are as ſo many Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, if not of the paſt or of the preſent, at leaſt of the time to come: for in this infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſpace of time and of the World, all that which can happen meets with its time and its place.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, Hiſtory being a kind of Experience, 'tis certain, that we may profit much by it; beſides, there are ſome of them which come from ſo good hands, that though we know them, 'tis a pleaſure to us to read them. Kings do well to read them, and alſo to inform themſelves of things which paſs in their own times, that they may have an eye to what may be done therein, and not loſe any opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or advantages. 'Tis principally neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to bring the young Prince to conſider that thoſe Kings and Emperours who have been worthy men, beſides the glory which remains to them, that they led alſo a moſt happy and pleaſant life.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:98279:29"/>
But the beſt time for taking the Air is almoſt paſt, and methinks it were good to go and take two or three turns by the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſide: Let us go (ſaid the Mareſhal) I had not thought of it, if you had not put me in mind.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:98279:29"/>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>THE THIRD CONVERSATION.</head>
               <p>THE Chevalier came in good time to the Mareſhals Lodgings, who had a mind to go forth that morning, there being neither wind nor heat, but one of thoſe pleaſant days which are not too light nor too gloomy. The Mareſhal was alone in his Chamber leaning againſt the Window which looks upon the Gardens, and ſeeing the Chevalier come in, he told him with a chearful countenance, that he took it kindly that he forſook not his Friend at a time of need, and that he had thoughts of taking the Air, it being ſuch fine Weather; and that he ſhould be glad to have ſo good Company. The Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier anſwered, He was very ſorry that it was no better. I doubt it not (ſaid the Mareſhal ſmiling) you are the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it. One ought to wiſh himſelf of an agreeable Converſation, if it were
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98279:30"/>
only to entertain himſelf: For a man is ſometimes alone, and when he is tired with his own thoughts, he cannot be rid of them as he would. That happens to me but too often (ſaid the Chevalier) and even at this inſtant that I am ſpeaking to you, I am glad to be with you; for I find that if I were alone, I ſhould be but little ſatisfied with any thing that comes into my mind. That which you tell me doth not at all pleaſe me (replied the Mareſhal) for as a man always loves himſelf a little, ſo he is apt to flatter himſelf, and when he is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his own thoughts, what likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is there that others ſhould be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, who for the moſt part excuſe nothing? But I will not be ſo nice: and walking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Garden, Come let us not droop (ſaid he) ſpeaking in a pleaſant manner; for by ſtirring we animate our vigour and ſpirits.</p>
               <p>There were in this Garden Orange-trees full of flowers, the ſight and odour of which rejoyced and pleaſed them. They fetched ſome turns in the Walks, entertaining themſelves on divers Subjects, and after that, being ſet down under the Orange-trees; Let us enjoy this retirement, ſaid
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98279:30"/>
the Mareſhal, and taſte the ſweet repoſe which is offered us, and entertain our ſelves in freedom. Methinks, ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, that one lives more in two days of pleaſure, and are more ſenſible what life is, than in two years full of buſineſs and trouble. I find alſo that we ſee greater things in retirement, than abroad in the World, or at leaſt we conſider them better. For what do we ſee of great in the World, unleſs it be perhaps an Army, the Siege of a Town, or the Court of a Prince? We are quickly accuſtomed to them, and all this appears great to us only at the firſt ſight. But if we look upon the different works of Nature, the Sun ſetting, a ſtill night, and theſe Planets which ſo majeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally rowl over our heads, we are continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally admiring them. Thoſe who think only of their Fortune, are imployed about a little artificial World which they underſtand ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well; but this great natural World is unknown to them.</p>
               <p>But for all that, replied the Mareſhal, it is this little World that makes men great, or to ſpeak more properly, which makes them be known. For thoſe who are not ſo, of whatſoever merit they are, dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98279:31"/>
any notice taken that they have ever lived. Beſides, conſider with your ſelf, that there is ſuch a Prince, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he hath been once ſeen, makes one deſirous to ſee him again, and whom the moſt agreeable ſolitude cannot make one forget. That kind of life is like an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment, I cannot but have an eye that way; and the young Prince being always in my thoughts, I muſt needs aſk you whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you think he ought to be ſo tenderly bred, and withal what care is uſually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for the bringing up ſuch perſons as are ſo dear to us?</p>
               <p>My opinion, anſwered the Chevalier, as to that is, that there ſhould be a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard had to his conſtitution; but I ſhould like it better to have it done in a manner a little more hardy, than ſo much of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, provided that it be without any danger. We are ſo careful (ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal) how to ſecure the preſent, that we hazard the future. I have ſeen many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who by too great a choiceneſs have been loſt; they have been bred ſo, as that they could not endure any thing of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, nor the leaſt diſorder. They went to bed and roſe always at a conſtant
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98279:31"/>
hour, (and you know whether the World allows any one to live after that manner) and when they had occaſion to alter their courſe of life, they had not been two months in the Army, but they were dead or dying: Whereas others who had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times accuſtomed themſelves to any thing, were as well there as elſewhere, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times better.</p>
               <p>I believe, ſaid the Chevalier, one can never break ones ſelf of it, when one hath been delicately bred, and even the ſpirit and the heart may be infected by it. Alſo in my judgment, it were well if a Prince did know how ſometimes to put off all that which we call Pomp and Magnificence; for there is nothing which it needleſs and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, which becomes not at laſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary by accuſtoming ones ſelf to it. Not that thoſe ſhould be hearkned to, who grumble ſo much againſt plenty and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and who will not allow of gildings nor of rich Furniture? Moſt part of ſuch ſort of people know not what they would have, and the reſt pretend to get them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves an eſteem by contemning that which they have not in their power. It is well enough known, that the Carvings and fret
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98279:32"/>
Works ſo finely painted, and the Tapeſtries emboſſed with gold, can charm neither grief nor melancholy; and that one is the leſs ſubject to fumes, when one ſees nothing but the greenneſs of the fields, and that thoſe magnificent Beds hinder us not from thinking the nights many times very tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. It is well enough known, that riches are of little value, and likewiſe that they may be hurtful: Not that the evil is in the having them, but in the thinking our ſelves the more worthy for them, or in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dejected when we have them not. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Honeſty is far above them all; and if we ſhould come to want every thing, and be reduced to ſuffer much, we ſhould not think our ſelves diſhonoured by it, no more than if we were ſick, or of a weak conſtitution.</p>
               <p>You take it right, ſaid the Mareſhal, and I think that by degrees there might be ſome little attempts made to give our Prince the knowledge, or at leaſt the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of certain things which Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren uſe not to entertain themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and which ſurpaſſeth their ordinary ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities. For although a Child underſtands not at the firſt what is ſaid to him in its
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98279:32"/>
proper and full ſignification, it prepares him againſt another time; they are as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Eſſays of Reaſon, which never comes all at once.</p>
               <p>I would not exerciſe him in imaginary Subjects nor nice Notions. For that which is ſaid, if it be unſeaſonable, or too far fetched, affects but very little, and leaves but confuſed impreſſions. The ſmalleſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion which is offered ſufficeth to ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that bears ſome weight and pleaſeth. For I find that it is of conſequence, that they ſtudy to form his wit agreeably. The pleaſure he will take to hearken and to look upon him, will likewiſe make him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to be inſtructed; and if the perſons who are about him, have a grace in their actions and their words, he will retain at leaſt the manner how he ought to behave and expreſs himſelf. If you conſider it well, this agreeable way of communicating ones ſelf to others is of no ſmall conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. It is very material (ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier) and as you intimated before, the ſureſt way to acquire that ſo agreeable and taking a way, is to frequent the company of thoſe that have it and practiſe it. It conſiſts moſt commonly in things ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98279:33"/>
that though we are ſenſible of them, we can ſcarce ſay what they are. You made uſe of one expreſſion that pleaſed me infinitely to form the mind: I remember ſome that were good Maſters, who taught the Exerciſes in ſo great exactneſs, that there was nothing defective or ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: not the leaſt time loſt, nor the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt motion that was not neceſſary to acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thoſe Maſters told me, that if once our bodies were made and formed, the reſt would not coſt much pains. So it ſeems to me, that thoſe who have their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings formed, underſtand all that is ſaid to them, and that they want after that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome body to put them in mind. When we meet with ſuch, and keep them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, we take certain opinions and certain obſervations, which we ſhould never have of our ſelves, and I ſee nothing which can contribute ſo much as that to the making of a great man.</p>
               <p>You touch me very ſenſibly, cryed the Mareſhal, if they had in my youth diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to me that which I have ſince found out by my own experience and reflections, how much time and pains had they ſaved me? one word from them to the purpoſe
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98279:33"/>
had made me comprehend a world of things, that I am ſure I know not, nor ſhall never know whilſt I live. I reflect on all thoſe opportunities which I have loſt, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all thoſe things which I might have done, and which I was not aware of till it was too late. You cannot imagine how I blame my ſelf for thoſe many ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ps, which I had not made, if any one had lent me his hand. All the World commits faults, even the moſt able perſons, but the greateſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are perceived.</p>
               <p>He ſpake with ſo much earneſtneſs, that the Chevalier ſaid to him, Sir, we muſt in all things comfort our ſelves with this, that this life is not worth ſo much, that we ſhould thus trouble our ſelves in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we paſs it. We are ready to leave the World when we begin to underſtand it well, or at leaſt we are very far on our Journey afore we have learnt the beſt way. You have great reaſon in what you ſay (anſwered the Mareſhal) but let them not alledge, that 'tis neceſſary we muſt be of ſuch an age to underſtand to ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and that good ſenſe cannot come but by a long experience. A Child that hath ingenuity will comprehend all that is ſaid
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:98279:34"/>
to him when the right means is uſed, and that they accommodate themſelves to his Genius.</p>
               <p>I agree to it, ſaid the Chevalier, but I would not over-burden him with a long chain of inſtruction, nor ſo methodical. I rather chuſe to ſpeak to him but of a few things, and let each Precept work its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and commend or blame him according as he ſhould give occaſion for either, and ſtill give him a reaſon for all I told him, in ſuch a manner that he might come of his own accord inſenſibly to make the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it to himſelf. It is much better to enlighten his Underſtanding rather than charge his Memory. Beſides, too many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Precepts are forgotten before one can make uſe of them. They refer you to a time when (ſay they) you ſhall ſee rare things, but this time is a great while a coming.</p>
               <p>They ſhould ſo order it, that all that they ſay and teach to the young Prince, may render him more knowing and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to day than he was yeſterday, and ſo that you your ſelf may be ſenſible of the progreſs he makes. Beſides, it were good to accuſtom him to be free and affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98279:34"/>
which are vertues that make people love great Kings. Affection produceth ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects which are very peculiar to it ſelf.</p>
               <p>How true is that (cryed the Mareſhal) and of what conſequence it is for a young Prince to have the Art of making himſelf to be beloved? I prize it above all (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Chevalier) how much do you think this noble height and elevation of the mind and underſtanding contributes to it? You hit upon that which is of greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance (ſaid the Mareſhal) and for that reaſon ſo ſoon as he had learned that which is uſually taught in his firſt years, I would begin to give him ſome new light of things, I would enlarge his knowledge, and ſhew him every thing. But for fear of carrying him out of the way, and of ſtraggling into ſome unknown Country, I would have a great care to chuſe good Guides, and the beſt of them ſhould not eſcape me.</p>
               <p>Children, ſaid the Chevalier, are not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſpeculative, the moſt part of them are active, and carried away with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; yet there are ſome that are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſerious enough, and are capable to retire into themſelves. It were to be wiſht that the young Prince be neither too ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98279:35"/>
nor too active. It is the eveneſt and beſt temper to partake of both, and to be able to paſs with eaſe from the one to the other. For the mind and ſpirit by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual thinking, is apt to ſink within it ſelf; and if it remain ſo any long time, it becomes ſullen and leſs proper for the World. Perpetual action without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion produceth all outward, and thoſe who continually practiſe it, make no refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xions, and never come to be eminent men.</p>
               <p>Though we have but few moments of leiſure, we ought to ſpend them in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what we intend to do; for by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating we find out the ways to arrive to perfection; but when we believe that we have found them, it is neceſſary to put them in practice, that we may know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are right; for we cannot be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or aſſured of it but by our own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. If that which we fancy to our ſelves to be the way to ſucceed in a buſineſs, be but a meer Idæa, or ſome invention too difficult to put in practice, we need only make a tryal, and we ſhall quickly unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves. By that means we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove every day, and ſtill add new perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98279:35"/>
to that which we do beſt.</p>
               <p>When I came firſt to the Court, ſaid the Mareſhal, every body thought that to be an accompliſhed man. There was nothing requiſite but Dancing well, running the Ring, or ſomething of this nature; every one choſe that which he liked beſt, and ſet himſelf to it, as if it had been his Trade.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſort of things add a grace to a man when he well performs them, as well as they do at all other times; I mean that the body is the freer, and not ſo ſtiff, and their ſkill in thoſe Exerciſes is perceived, although they ſtand ſtill. You know it is a great advantage to be a good Actor<hi>:</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſaid the Chevalier, is a kind of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and as words well choſen are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable when they expreſs things that pleaſe, ſo all which is expreſt by the face or geſture of the body, is well received when it is done with a good grace. But we muſt not miſtake, there are thoſe that are ſometimes Actors of nothing, as well as Speakers of nothing. Action hath its defects as well as the Language, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in both, we muſt obſerve in all ſubjects that which will beſt pleaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:98279:36"/>
This Talent of being a good Actor ſeems to me very neceſſary for perſons that live abroad in the World, and it is much like that which is called now adays (to ſpeak <hi>à la Mode) Having a good Air;</hi> but it is not only in that, that the good Air ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, it hath an influence and ſpreads it ſelf upon every thing, and to ſay in a word what it is, it conſiſts in doing well that which we do. People confound it many times with the word <hi>Agrément,</hi> although there is very much difference between them. The <hi>good Air</hi> ſhews it ſelf at the firſt; it is more regular and more in order. <hi>Agrément</hi> is more flattering and inſinuating; it goes more directly to the heart, and by more ſecret ways: The good Air gives more admiration, and the <hi>Agrément</hi> more of Love. Young people who are not as yet perfect, commonly have not the good Air nor certain <hi>Agréments</hi> like thoſe who are maſters of it.</p>
               <p>Some people who take pleaſure to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſaid the Mareſhal, (ſmiling) like very well ſuch Subjects as theſe, to ſhew their Wit in, but it is not altogether ſo pleaſant to thoſe that hear them; but when any one underſtands well that which he
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98279:36"/>
aims at, he ſays nothing that is imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and his Reaſon and Learning are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable enough.</p>
               <p>Now to return to our ancient Courtiers, as the moſt part of Exerciſes are only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for a certain Age; it happens, that thoſe who had addicted themſelves only to them, when their Youth was paſt, they knew no longer how to imploy themſelves. Therefore I would not wiſh any to depend principally on ſuch Exerciſes<hi>:</hi> I know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well that they are not to be neglected, but there is ſomething which is better. In effect, I have always believed that one ſhould not ſo much wiſh for any thing as for Wit, and many times people fail of it by their own fault<hi>:</hi> And I am now more of that opinion than I was, that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible not to have it, if one be brought up in the Company of ſome people.</p>
               <p>At leaſt, added the Chevalier, a late eminent Philoſopher holds, that all the World naturally have very near the ſame capacity: and that the principal difference proceeds only from the care that is taken to form it, or elſe from the courſe and bent that people take of themſelves.</p>
               <p>I cannot altogether agree to that (ſaid
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98279:37"/>
the Mareſhal) the advantage is to be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to a happy birth in the firſt place, and Art afterwards perfects it. As to the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by ones ſelf, it ſeldom happens, that the mind without ſome help takes the beſt courſes to do it; and I wonder at ſome Princes who are nevertheleſs excellent men, although in their Youth they have been taught but very few things. The moſt part of thoſe who are about them fancy, that it is not good to proceed too haſtily, and that it might prejudice their health; which I ſhould like well enough, provided that there be regard had to the conſequences, and that they conſider how dangerous it may be, to accuſtom a young Prince to be without Wit. Wherefore they muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to inſtruct him in a pleaſant way, and be always teaching him ſomething without tiring him.</p>
               <p>But to return to thoſe Princes who are the moſt admired, and who have formed and inſtructed themſelves, I do not ſee that we can eſtabliſh any Maxims upon ſo few Examples: Neither am I of the opinion (ſaid the Chevalier) that any one ſhould relye upon it, and I believe that the ſureſt way to accompliſh ones ſelf, is to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98279:37"/>
to well-bred perſons; as the voice improves by ſinging, and one learns how to order it with ſkill by practiſing under a good Maſter; ſo Wit inſinuates and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates it ſelf inſenſibly amongſt perſons who truly have it. There is no doubt but it may be acquired, if an able man ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it.</p>
               <p>It ſhould therefore be my advice (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the Chevalier) that thoſe who have Wit, and are well-bred men, be not only well received by this Prince, but likewiſe that care be taken to find them out and draw them thither; for commonly they are not Traders, nor forward to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: they know how to content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their own Fortune; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, they are ſo rarely met with, that thoſe who underſtand them well need not fear to be troubled with too many of them. I do not remember that I ever in my life ſaw ſo great a number of them at one time, but I could have wiſhed them more.</p>
               <p>This ſort of people always ſay ſomething that pleaſeth, and never do any thing which hath not ſome mark of Worth and Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and by converſing with, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98279:38"/>
them, we not only inform our ſelves of ſuch things as are neceſſary to be known for the making of an accompliſht man, but alſo we learn how to apply them, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſo far as to know when 'tis proper and mannerly to be ſilent. Yet we ſee ſuch perſons ſometimes, without taking notice of this worth in them; they put me in mind of the beſt Artiſts, who are leſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward than the others, and that proceed not ſo much from a lazineſs or negligence in them, as from a certain averſion which the moſt part of well-bred perſons have to ſet a value upon themſelves.</p>
               <p>When I chance to meet with any ſuch perſons, I know how to diſtinguiſh them; and though I hear very good things come from them, and they behave themſelves with as much becomingneſs as can be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I make no concluſion from thence; for many times this is but a borrowed Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and the actings of a Part, I always take notice whether there be a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and whether there be nothing that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts. In ſhort, I regard not ſo much that which appears ſo polite and regular, as I do certain other things which ſhews that the Underſtanding goes further, and is of a larger extent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:98279:38"/>
Children ſeek not always the company of Children; thoſe who are of a bold am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious nature love to be amongſt men, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if they be pleaſant. In my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they ſhould accuſtom the young Prince to divert himſelf amongſt ſuch; one cannot imagine a more ſure and leſs pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful way to render him the moſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed Prince of the World, than the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving even in his youth ſuch Courtiers?</p>
               <p>For as a Child without any ſtudy learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Tongue of thoſe people whom he hears ſpeak, and afterwards ſpeaks it na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally; ſo he will not fail to learn inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly the manners and actions of thoſe who are about him, and all that he gains in that manner becomes natural to him. They ſhould make uſe, as much as is poſſible, (anſwered the Mareſhal) of this way of inſtructing him; but that alone is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to teach him to ſpeak well; for to effect that, 'tis neceſſary to mix a little of Art and Study. I acknowledge that (ſaid the Chevalier) and indeed one cannot have too much of either of them; but we muſt make it our principal buſineſs to put into him ſuch a kind of Wit, which I cannot expreſs, and which neither Books nor Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98279:39"/>
men can hardly ever give him. It ſeems to me, that thoſe who have it want neither Art nor Learning: and when one hath it not, however compleat one may be in any thing, there is almoſt always ſome unhappy circumſtance which ſpoils that which one does beſt. It ſeems then, that to the compleating of an honeſt worthy man, there is nothing neceſſary but well ſpeaking and well doing.</p>
               <p>Speaking well is what we are diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of; when we have learned all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of a Tongue, with ſuch other things as are taught in relation to well ſpeaking, all this is nothing, in truth, if we know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but this; for what probability is there of perſwading or pleaſing knowing perſons, or what likelihood of getting an intereſt in them, unleſs we underſtand how to touch them, and can hit upon the right way to gain them? The moſt part of the great Maſters (if you obſerve them) ſay not a word of this.</p>
               <p>Without this knowledge (ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal) it would be difficult to ſucceed well, eſpecially in the Commerce of the World, where the leaſt failings are taken notice of. When this misfortune happens, we cannot
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98279:39"/>
recover our ſelves when we would; and I ſee that it is of the greateſt importance to have this ſort of Wit, and to underſtand the World very well. I believe neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that it would be very difficult to ſpeak well upon all ſorts of Subjects with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either Art or Rules.</p>
               <p>This Art (ſaid the Chevalier) is eaſily learned, and is but a ſmall matter (at leaſt in the manner it is uſually taught) the moſt part of thoſe who know it, are but little the more able for it. Whether it be that the Precepts which have been given them are not very good, or that they have not been taught to make uſe of them as they ought. If inſtructions that were excellent were given, and they made practiſe them well as they gave them, it would without doubt be a great help to well ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>As for the Rules that are to be given, they muſt follow exactly thoſe that are in uſe; the moſt part of thoſe Rules regard the purity of the Language, and I find that many perſons without having learned them, do notwithſtanding put them in practice. There are other Rules that extend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves further, which Reaſon and long Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience have made ſo. They are things
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98279:40"/>
which the Maſters of that Art have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from that which has ſometimes ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded well, and for that reaſon they thought that they might give them for Rules; but they are very often ſo uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that they are not to be made uſe of, but according as one finds or judges them to the purpoſe; and if any one ties himſelf to them, he muſt have a regard to time and circumſtances. So that if any one by his induſtry or by chance ſhould diſcover ſomething that is better and more than hath hitherto been ſeen, he ought to make uſe of his own diſcoveries and invention.</p>
               <p>The beſt Art which makes us excel in ſpeaking, ſhews it ſelf only under a natural dreſs and appearance, it likes plain and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural beauty; but (and though it endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make its beauty and perfections to appear in their proper and beſt light) it contrives principally how to hide it ſelf. Do you remember thoſe enchanted Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the Palace of <hi>Armide?</hi>
               </p>
               <q>E quel che'l bello, e'l caro accreſce à l'opre, L'art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> che tutto fà nulla ſi ſcopre.</q>
               <p>I find that thoſe who are the moſt perfect,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98279:40"/>
ſhew themſelves leaſt, and when things ſmell of Art and Study, we may conclude that thoſe who ſay them have but little of either, or elſe that they know not how to make uſe of them. This is the fault of people who ſpeak ſo, that they cannot be underſtood by any (though they have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much Wit) unleſs they be learned: But as for thoſe who underſtand not as they ought, by reaſon of their little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or that they are not acquainted with the World, they muſt blame only themſelves for it.</p>
               <p>But this is a great deal for one ſitting, if you have a mind to walk again, I perceive amongſt theſe Orange-trees an Alley where you will find it cool. I ſee well (ſaid the Mareſhal riſing up) that we ſhall diſcourſe no more for to day, let us fetch two or three turns, and then to Dinner; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me, my ſtomach begins to call: And after Dinner we will go to <hi>M.L.G.</hi> where we will play all day. I was ſo pleaſed with our Walk yeſterday, that I muſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry you thither again to morrow, not to the ſame place, but on the other ſide of the River upon that riſing Hill, I will come to your Lodgings, and if you are within, we will go to the Hermitage.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:98279:41"/>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>THE FOURTH CONVERSATION.</head>
               <p>ACcording to his promiſe the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal came to call the Chevalier a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout four or five of the Clock in the Evening. It was fair Weather, but a little hot, according to the ſeaſon; they quickly came to the Hermitage, which is but half a mile from the Town. There is a Cell and a Chappel with a Garden to it; they could not get in, becauſe that no Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite lived there, and the two Religious men which were uſed to be there were gone forth that day, the Mareſhal and the Chevalier went down a little further into the Wood, where the Trees a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were very thick and tufted. Under this thickneſs (which the Sun could not penetrate) they walked upon the Turf, as in a Meadow where the graſs begins but juſt to peep forth.</p>
               <p>After they had walked a while, they
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:98279:41"/>
ſtayed and ſate down under an old Oak extremely thick, And what ſhall we ſay, cryed the Mareſhal, or rather what ſhall we not ſay, I have ſpent the night at play where you left me, ſaid the Chevalier, and that hath made me very dull. I did not perceive it, ſaid the Mareſhal, though we diſcourſed by the way. The Coach kept me ſtirring, ſaid the Chevalier, now I am at quiet, the freſhneſs of this Wood makes me drowſie: I am ſometimes as you are now, anſwered the Mareſhal, and when I am in that condition, methinks I feel a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſweetneſs, which is found between ſleeping and waking, and I think of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, only I am ſenſibly much pleaſed; but commonly I put it by, that I may be good Company, and beſides one ſleeps the better for it at night.</p>
               <p>You told me as you were coming along, continued the Mareſhal, that thoſe perſons who expreſs themſelves beſt, uſe repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons oftner than others, and yet it is thought a defect in them. Is there not ſomething of contradiction in that? I remember it, ſaid the Chevalier, and I do not think my ſelf miſtaken in it, that is, becauſe people who ſpeak well, make uſe at firſt of the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98279:42"/>
beſt words and Phraſes to expreſs their thoughts, and when there is occaſion to touch again upon the ſame things (as it often happens) although they know very well that Variety pleaſeth, yet it is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom to them to quit the beſt expreſſion to make uſe of a worſe<hi>:</hi> whereas thoſe who are not ſo curious, make uſe of the firſt that preſents it ſelf; ſo that Chance gives a Variety to their Language. And becauſe we are quickly tired with one man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſpeaking (although it be the exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt) to make that which it ſignifies to be underſtood, we are apt to think it ſome defect, and thoſe who ſpeak purely, are more ſubject to it than the others; for there is a good and evil in all things, and ſo there is in Language, which in ſome kind cannot be too pure, but diverſity is leſs tireſom, and the meaneſt word can find a fit place, our Tongue abounds not ſo much in words, that we need to reject it.</p>
               <p>Some Ladies who have an admirable Wit, and who ought to make uſe of it, to do Juſtice to every thing, condemn ſome very good words, which 'tis almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be without. Thoſe perſons are they who uſe them too often, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98279:42"/>
to little purpoſe, that have given them this averſion; but though we muſt ſubmit to the Judgment, and likewiſe to the aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thoſe Ladies, yet for all that, I think it were not amiſs to appeal ſometimes to ſo many excellent men, who judge ſoundly and without caprice, and who have had meetings ſo long to decide concerning Language. I think it ſo, ſaid the Mareſhal, and it is not a buſineſs to be neglected; for the ſweeteſt moments of our life paſs in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining one another, and very few things are done without ſpeaking; and I find by experience, that it is a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to ſucceed in it<hi>:</hi> But that in it which appears to me of the greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance is, that occaſions are offered, wherein we have need of ſkill and wit to gain people, and to make them underſtand that one is in the right<hi>:</hi> people content themſelves with the being able to acquit themſelves tolerably well in this, which I have been ſpeaking of; and the moſt part of them are perſwaded, that if they can do a thing well, it is no hard matter to do it a little better, whereas in truth therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts that which we call Perfection, and is the only difference between excellent
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98279:43"/>
Work-men and ordinary.</p>
               <p>You have quite awakened me, ſaid the Chevalier, with this word, <hi>a little better,</hi> which appears to me very difficult; but how happy is one that is able to attain to it! And I am of your Judgment, that it cannot be too much endeavoured in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, it is the ſureſt means to make our ſelves to be beloved; beſides, I find that when we pleaſe other perſons well, we are likewiſe the better pleaſed with our ſelves, and thereon depends the greateſt happineſs of our life.</p>
               <p>As to thoſe opportunities and occaſions, of which you ſpeak, wherein thoſe who are the ſkilfulleſt for the moſt part carry it, I am of opinion, that the beſt words and ways we can invent to perſwade are not good, but ſo far only as they are decent and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and that we ſhould not deſire to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like barbarous Princes on any terms, but like the Heroes in ſuch a manner as may pleaſe even the vanquiſhed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>I find nothing ſo commendable, as to have an upright and ſincere heart; that ſeems to be the foundation of Wiſdom, or at leaſt all wicked people are by me ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98279:43"/>
of folly. It is impoſſible to have a noble and well framed mind, but it muſt be ſomewhat acroſs and contrary to the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the World; and even in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of the moſt violent paſſions, ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will through them diſcern that which is moſt honeſt, and love it beſt.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who have an upright heart, their Judgment, how ſmall ſoever, will be the ſame; and obſerve always, that thoſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who have ſo many turnings and dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in their heart, never have a right Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: there is always ſome counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit light which gives them falſe appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and then their artifices and craft ſhew that they have not parts enough to effect their deſigns by fair and honeſt ways, the way that pleaſes worthy perſons, is that of freedom and plain dealing.</p>
               <p>What a Gracefulneſs ſo clear a Source gives to all the actions of our lives! how it beautifies our words and thoughts! and how aimable a thing it is to ſpeak well, when ſo much ſincerity goes along with it! One may not perhaps be happy in all things in following this Maxime (neither are thoſe ſo who are biaſſed to their own intereſt) at the leaſt one is ſure to gain
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98279:44"/>
the eſteem and affection of thoſe who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand true merit, and what can one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire more?</p>
               <p>As the Chevalier was ſpeaking, he took notice that the Marſhal wholly gave himſelf up to hearken to him, &amp; fearing leſt ſo much attention might be hurtful to him, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to divert him by ſome pleaſant digreſſion. The Mareſhal, who perceived it, I ſee very well, ſaid he, that you are willing to favour my health, but you take not the right way. Every one muſt be dealt with according to that ſpirit that is in them: you muſt accommodate your ſelf to every palate; that which is a diverſion to moſt people, is tedious to me, ſenſe and reaſon never tire me: thoſe things more eſpecially which may make me more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and accompliſhed, always pleaſe me. Well then, let us continue, ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, one would not have thought you ſo ſerious.</p>
               <p>Amongſt perſons of rare merit, of whom I have ſome Idæa; I ſee ſome of them who behave themſelves ſo nobly in every thing, that they undertake they cannot be thought on without admiration, and I take notice alſo of others who ſpeak in ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98279:44"/>
a manner, that it is very hard to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to it; however one ſhould ſtrive to equal them both in the one and the other, and if it be poſſible to ſurpaſs them: for be it in acting or in ſpeaking, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which is not of this value, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be loved and admired. When the heart and brain are full of theſe thoughts, and people accuſtomed to them from their infancy, from thence we may juſtly expect ſomething very rare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to be produced.</p>
               <p>We need not trouble our ſelves whether all neceſſary conſequences are made good. It imports not much whether one be at the firſt ſo equal or ſo regular, provided that the manner be ſo fair and noble, that thoſe who conſider it, cannot ſay how one may go; with a little care and time one arrives at perfection, and it ſeems, that Fortune her ſelf takes delight to compleat any thing which is well begun. I know ſome who ſpeak well, and commit none of thoſe we call faults, but it is always in the ſame tone: we know what we are to expect from them; and in my judgment there is nothing we ſhould ſo much endeavour to avoid as the not having ſomething extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98279:45"/>
in our diſcourſe. It may ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that 'tis for want of a good occaſion that we ſay nothing that is excellent, and the ſubject may not permit it. Yet for all this there is no ſubject ſo untoward, which may not be turned to ſome pleaſant ſenſe by thoſe who know how to make good uſe of their Wit. For that which for the moſt part ſeems difficult to me, and even impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, is not ſo much in it ſelf, as becauſe of our little ſkill and invention; for peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might do many things that would cauſe aſtoniſhment, if they had induſtry enough to diſcover the ways of doing it; and 'tis certain, that there are ſuch ways, though they are not always found out.</p>
               <p>While people are young, they cannot judge rightly of any thing, and if it comes to paſs, that either by experience, reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or the meeting with ſome intelligent perſons, they come to be of another mind, they deſpiſe that which they once ſo much admired, and many times they laugh at themſelves, when they examine themſelves without flattery. But if any one knew the juſt value of every thing aright, do you not think that he would divert himſelf, and make good ſport with thoſe people
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98279:45"/>
that are cryed up, at leaſt with thoſe that preſume, and have a great opinion of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? As for the reſt who ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſmall matters, and have hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thoughts of themſelves, one cannot laugh at them, although they do amiſs, becauſe they know that all the World is capable of committing the like errours, and they act upon that Maxime.</p>
               <p>And ſo, though we have but a glimpſe, or do but fancy ſomething better than that which we ſpeak, yet we muſt have a little confidence to expreſs it well and with a good grace. But nothing is ſo great a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to the attaining perfection, as the belief that one hath already found it.</p>
               <p>It comes into my mind (ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal ſmiling) that the more perfect one is, the more this that we ſay may be uſeful, and that our entertainments are almoſt like (if the compariſon offends you not) the Commentaries of <hi>Cæſar,</hi> by which no body could much profit, unleſs he were a great Souldier before. For we touch by the by only on that which offers it ſelf as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the making of a worthy honeſt man. What we ſay concerns thoſe only who are animated with ſuch a kind of Spirit as we
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98279:46"/>
are; as for the reſt, they will never go very far. But do you think that this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit may be acquired? If you judge it may, how would you begin to infuſe it into Children? for one muſt not pretend to begin with them ſo high at the firſt.</p>
               <p>It were to be wiſhed, that thoſe who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducate Children, ſaid the Chevalier, would endeavour to make them love or hate that which deſerves the one or the other, I mean as much as Childhood will permit, and to order it ſo, that they may have a good taſte or diſcernment. For to expreſs my ſelf well, I muſt make uſe of this word, which ſo many people abuſe, a good taſte would make him underſtand what he ought to deſire to learn, and the means to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in it<hi>:</hi> For if he had afore-hand a right apprehenſion of good and of evil, the very courſe of things would inſtruct him without a Governour, and likewiſe the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to that which is evil, whenever he ſaw it, would be a ſufficient Leſſon to him to avoid it.</p>
               <p>One cannot have too curious a taſte to diſcern between true and falſe pleaſures, and not be deceived in what pleaſes or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſes. That which I mean by it is, not
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98279:46"/>
to diſreliſh every thing, like a ſick perſon, but to be able to judge well of any thing that preſents it ſelf I know not by what a kind of apprehenſion (which I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs) which works quicker, and is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more in the right, than reflections are; but for all that we muſt not reject too ſeverely that which is diſpleaſing, or be too buſie with our reproofs. The moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable way of inſtructing and reforming others, is to endeavour to do that well our ſelves, which we ſee them do ill, by which means we make our life the more eaſie. Beſides, I would have it ſo ordered, that a young mans wit and heart be diſpoſed as it ought to be. Wit finds out the means to attain to perfection, and the heart is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to put in practice that which we judge to be beſt; for honeſty is not a meer ſpeculation, 'tis fit it ſhould be active and govern.</p>
               <p>We ſee many Children, ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal, who are not without ſome prudence and a fore-ſight of what may be either hurtful or beneficial to them; but that which is called the having a good taſte (for I dare uſe this word as well as you all the elegant ways of ſpeaking, when
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98279:47"/>
they are not affected, and are well appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are becoming enough) I ſay, that which I called the having a good taſte, muſt not be expected from young people, unleſs they are born with a much more than an ordinary Genius, or that there hath been a great care had in their Education. I do not know whence that proceeds, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be, that by a natural inſtinct, they take at firſt to that which appears to them the moſt neceſſary, and that the reſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects them but very little.</p>
               <p>This is an excellent reaſon which you give, ſaid the Chevalier, and I look upon it as a hard matter for one that is young not to be tranſported with that which ſparkles, and makes the beſt ſhew, there ſhould be as much care as could be taken to undeceive Children, becauſe that it is natural to them as well as to the people in general to love Shows; and even theſe who are born Princes, they are inclined na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally to delight in Stage-plays and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Spectacles. But thoſe that are perfect, and that have a good judgment, regard not things of ſhew, when they are but of little worth; thoſe which are but of little lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre and great prize, pleaſe them. That is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98279:47"/>
to be taken notice of in all things, even in our thoughts and underſtandings; for if thoſe ſorts of things ſeem very fine, they are ſo only in appearance, and preſently diſliked; thoſe that are ſo in reality, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out appearance, the more they are conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, the better they are liked: the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe they are fair of themſelves, without any helps or ornaments, and that ſtill we diſcover ſome new and ſecret gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in them, which were not at the firſt perceived.</p>
               <p>How comes it to paſs, ſaid the Mareſhal, that ſome people who expreſs themſelves well upon ſome certain Subjects, differ ſo much from themſelves, when they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to diſcourſe of other things? and do not admire you that that man (whom we have both known, and who had ſo much Wit) hath left behind him ſuch ill Love-Letters, he who writ ſuch good ones on other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? How could that be? was it not ſtill one and the ſame Genius? It is indeed the ſame Genius, anſwered the Chevalier, but the moſt accompliſhed in the World is not able alike in all things, and diverſity of Subjects cauſe him to produce very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent effects.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:98279:48"/>
Beſides, to do a thing well, it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to know the manner of doing it, but we muſt take delight in it, and not be tired with it. We find that commonly good Maſters ſpeak well of that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to their own Trade, and I fancy to my ſelf, that this mans Trade was not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Love, or at leaſt that he never well underſtood what it was. It cannot be ſaid to be want of Wit, if his Letters concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love are not as his others ſo well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed, for there is in ſome of them more than enough; but the Wit was ill imployed, when his buſineſs was to touch the heart, he was thinking how to refine things, and ſhew his witty conceits. He writ to a Lady, with whom he was paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately in Love, that his Soul was ſo weak, that it had not ſtrength enough to go quite out of his body, that was the reaſon only which kept a little life in him: To another, that the only thing that hindred him from dying was, that he ſhould have ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in it, and that he reſolve he would not receive any in her abſence.</p>
               <p>He took theſe inventions from the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> and I make no doubt but they are good Models; but he made uſe of them
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:98279:48"/>
unſeaſonably. For this gallant and frolick manner of writing, which might be well received at the beginning of an Amour, was not ſeaſonable in the height of the fit, at which time people ſeldom uſe to droll and jeſt. Beſides, when he ſpeaks ſeriouſly he makes it his buſineſs chiefly to perſwade her of his Love, and that the quickeſt and beſt way to ſucceed is not to be ſo forward to declare ones Love. It were much more to the purpoſe for him to find out a way how to render his affection agreeable and acceptable to her. For a handſom Woman eaſily believes that ſhe doth not diſpleaſe, and I think ſhe is in the right, ſo that to tell her ſhe is handſom, and that we love her, need be the leaſt part of our care; ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not always to be loved, and the moſt important thing conſiſts in the ordering of it, ſo that if you did love her, ſhe might be very glad of it; we ought at leaſt to begin there. I find he very punctually examines all that paſſed in his heart, and to ſpeak my judgment, he ſhould remember that it is not the nature of violent paſſions to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon themſelves. A man that is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with anger, doth not think that he is in ſuch a fury, and one that is confounded
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98279:49"/>
with Love perceives not that he is ſo, or at leaſt if he do take notice of it, he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders himſelf no otherwiſe than in a natural eſtate, which he believes can never alter. I take notice alſo, that he doth ſo exagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate his grief and deſpair, that one may eaſily perceive that 'tis all falſe. It were much better to ſay leſs of it, and leave them the more to think. Beſides, Love ſhould be diſcerned a good while by the perſon beloved, without her being told of it, and above all, care muſt be taken not to make any complaint that ſavours of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice, or that may give any diſtruſt of what we ſay. That Adventure of <hi>Aſtræa</hi> and her Lover, who threw himſelf into the River <hi>Lignon,</hi> is eaſie and natural: They uſed no ſuch high ſtrains one to the other; their affection appeared not ſo much in their words, but all that was obſerved in them diſcovered it, and there never was any thing ſeen more tender and more affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>Beſides it ſeems to me, that there is no Subject that can leſs allow of falſe Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and that that perſon whom we men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, had ſometimes (contrary to his cuſtom) made uſe of ſome when he writ
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98279:49"/>
his Love-Letters; but that which was moſt diſpleaſing in him, was his too open and plain proceeding in that affair. The fair Goddeſs (ſaid an ancient <hi>Greek)</hi> doth not think well nor approve of any that ſpeak ſo openly of her Myſteries; and any one without being told it, may ſee that the veiling of them hath a good effect, and the expreſſions thereof cannot be too delicate and obſcure: witneſs this Verſe,</p>
               <q>I' en connois de plus miſerables?</q>
               <p>I find notwithſtanding, ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal, that this perſon hath done ſomething that is admirable in this kind, which agrees but ill with what you believe of him, that he was not moſt knowing in theſe matters. Can there be any thing more in perfection than that which is ſpoken to his Heroine? The praiſe of that, ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, is not wholly due to him<hi>:</hi> A Lady who gave him the deſign and the inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ought to have the greateſt ſhare of it. It is the ſame Lady whom he hath ſo well repreſented under the name of <hi>Zelide.</hi> The work was for ſome time in her hands afore any had ſeen it; that which hath ſo much
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98279:50"/>
charmed you comes from her, and you knowing her cannot wonder at it. You tell me a great deal of News, ſaid the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal, and perhaps you think that you have fully ſatisfied me; but I have ſtill one que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion more to aſk you.</p>
               <p>What is it that they mean by that high Eloquence which doth what it pleaſes, as ſo many people ſay? I have aſked ſome concerning it, who have bragged that they underſtood what it was, but never any one as yet could make me comprehend it. That which you aſk me, ſaid the Chevalier, is ſo little underſtood in the World, that even the word Eloquence might be ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: For it ſeems<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to me, that it is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom uſed but to play upon thoſe who are leſs pleaſed with good ſenſe than with a fine fantaſtical way of ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>It may be made uſe of in Raillery, ſaid the Mareſhal, but it would ſhew too much of niceneſs, and indeed of ignorance, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it altogether. Beſides, at the Court they ſeldom ſpeak of other things than what they ſee there, and thoſe kind of things in which every one eaſily intereſts himſelf and underſtands, makes that which is ſaid ſeem agreeable. But in ſuch retired
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98279:50"/>
places as theſe, if we did not entertain our ſelves on certain Subjects, which the Court trouble not themſelves withal, we ſhould ſpend our time but unpleaſantly.</p>
               <p>I agree to it, ſaid the Chevalier, and that which you aim at deſerves very well to be examined; but the moſt part of thoſe things which are conſidered rather by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion than by reaſon, are always ſomething doubtful, and this ſame is of that number, and ſo are all thoſe that concern the Graces, and likewiſe the Beauty, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the cauſe of this latter is leſs hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den than that of the Graces. If there were a diſpute concerning two handſom Women which of them was the moſt agreeable and faireſt, it would be hard to decide it, or at leaſt to make it ſo cleary appear, that all people in the World ſhould agree to it. One might ſay on ſuch an occaſion, ſuch a thing cauſes ſuch an effect in me; but I know not what others think of it. I take this to ſerve as an excuſe to my ſelf, if I am ſingular in my opinion.</p>
               <p>I do not think this high Eloquence to be ſo as it is imagined. People will have that it ought to amaze, and that it muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways a high ſtrain. And as they are of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98279:51"/>
that a plain and familiar ſtyle is low and mean; ſo they believe that others cannot appear naturally. If it ſhould be ſo too, 'tis becauſe they have more regard to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament than to the Excellency of the hing, and they do not conſider that they ſhould judge of it, as they do of gold, which is eſteemed according to its refinedneſs and purity.</p>
               <p>I ſhould be of a quite contrary Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe who will have it always ſtorming and thundering; and I think that it naturally loves to ſhew it ſelf without trouble and noiſe.</p>
               <p>As it is the fineſt and moſt noble, it is alſo the moſt difficult and leaſt common, it proceeds from a juſt and ſubtil diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but ſo high and of ſo large an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that there is nothing can be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove or beyond his. It is a fire pure and quick, and there are diſcovered by chance ſome glances of it, even in the moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and ordinary Converſations. Although it addreſſes it ſelf principally to the mind, and ſeems to make the gaining of that its only aim, yet it never fails to reach the heart. If any one indeed have a mind to perplex and put the Soul in diſorder, they
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:98279:51"/>
muſt take another way more ſenſible, and a more lively tone; but this high Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is not found but in the loftineſs of high conceptions. Thoſe who underſtand it only as that which is called a fine Style, do not take notice (if I miſtake not) of that which it hath moſt exquiſite in it. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in my judgment there muſt be a great ſtock of Beauty to ſupport great Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and it ſeldom happens, that people conceive things that require ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent way of expreſſing them. That which I have ſaid is a little intricate, and may not perhaps be well underſtood, peradventure it may be better apprehended in a more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar and known Subject.</p>
               <p>When Ladies have a mind to appear, as it were to vie with others in a great Aſſembly, you know they adorn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to pleaſe rather than to dazle the ſight: to ſome the richeſt attire is moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming, and to others the moſt modeſt; and commonly they avoid extremities, they ſtrive not to be too dull nor too glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering; we ſcarce ſee two in the ſame dreſs, and this variety is that which em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſheth the Scene.</p>
               <p>Since I am fallen upon this, I find that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98279:52"/>
the Eloquence which conceives well, and expreſſeth it ſelf ill, is much like a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Woman ill dreſſed, or in a careleſs habit; and that that which makes it ſelf not much to be conſidered as to Wit, but is very ready and dexterous as to the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, may reſemble a Woman paſſably handſom, but very exactly dreſt and ſet out, who for all her great care charms no body. But if wit and a ready clear ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion meddle, that is Beauty it ſelf, whereto nothing is wanting, and which pleaſeth in perfection.</p>
               <p>I am very much ſatisfied with the Idæa that you give me of it, ſaid the Mareſhal, and I conclude thereupon, that to expreſs ones ſelf well, one muſt endeavour to find out that in a Subject which is beſt and moſt agreeable; but not ſtrive ſo much to give a luſtre to the things that one ſays, as to place them in ſuch a manner which is moſt proper and beſt becomes them.</p>
               <p>I would not be too florid in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; it is a thing much to be wiſhed, that all that one ſays be good and fine, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Subject merits<hi>:</hi> but we muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by degrees: Nature is in that as in all other things, a very knowing Miſtreſs.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98279:52"/>
Conſider how ſhe proceeds inſenſibly, the faireſt day when it begins firſt to break and appear, hath ſo little light, that it is hardly diſcernable whether it be day or night. I diſcover all my thoughts to you, and if I am deceived, or take one thing for another, I hope you will take notice of it to me.</p>
               <p>In my mind nothing is ſo great a ſign, that the way of ſpeaking is noble, as when it leaves ſome certain things to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended without ſpeaking them: the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is clear enough, if one underſtands all that another ſays, although we do not at the firſt underſtand all that he thinks, or that his ſenſe extends it ſelf beyond his words.</p>
               <p>People many times ſeek out ſo many ſubtilties, and refine ſo upon a Subject, that that which was at firſt well ſaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes at laſt not ſo; when we have hit the point right, 'tis good to know when to give over, and to proceed to other matters: I would likewiſe give them ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther face and turn, becauſe diverſity ſeems not tedious.</p>
               <p>The perſon that ſpeaks ſhould accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate himſelf to the Underſtanding of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98279:53"/>
thoſe who hear him. The more Wit one has, the more he ought to be careful of it. Many times by thinking and ſpeaking things which few people have been uſed to hear, though they are expreſſed very clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they may be carried ſo high, that their heads may be giddy and turn round. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs this defect ſhould have its due, and I find it ſo ſeldom, that I meet with none that do complain of it, nor who are not glad of it; and at the worſt we may eaſily help it and break our ſelves of it.</p>
               <p>As to thoſe they call Jeſts or Sayings, I ſhould think that they depend not leſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſubject, nay even upon chance, than upon the underſtanding and wit; and that we muſt watch our time to bring them out. There is no great need of them, I think, and it is enough, if one ſpeaks like a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred honeſt man. That which is juſt and proper upon every occaſion that is offered, 'tis better far than fine conceits; yet for all that they are much liked, and I ſhould not wonder at it, if in effect they be good conceits; but I admire that Equivocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which have only the appearance of them, have brought people of very ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary wits into credit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:98279:53"/>
They affect to ſpeak Equivocations and Alluſions now adays, as heretofore they did to make Portraictures and Characters. For there is always, you know, ſome falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréments wherewith the World is abuſed.</p>
               <p>I think, ſaid the Chevalier, this to be a very ill invention; for to make ones ſelf be heard with pleaſure, one muſt ſay ſuch things as others will be glad to hear, and ſay them pleaſantly. I fancy that thoſe makers of Characters and Portraictures did neither of theſe. For the moſt part of thoſe whom they repreſented ſo curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, there was ſo little likeneſs, that the perſons could not be known. And beſides their manner and way of portraicting was not very good; for to make people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what they take notice of to be moſt rare or ſingular in them (whether it be that they would commend or leſſen them) there is a more noble and ſure way than to draw as they do, even to the ſmalleſt Lines.</p>
               <p>Excellent Painters never draw all; they always allow ſomething for you to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your imagination on, and ſtill leave them more to find out than they diſcover. That famous <hi>Greek</hi> ſo celebrated for his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98279:54"/>
Wit and Inventing, did not ſpend much of his time in deſcribing <hi>Helena.</hi> He ſaid not ſcarce any thing of her Face, nor of her Stature, and yet for all that he hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded all the World, that ſhe was the beautifulleſt Woman that ever was ſeen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taſſo,</hi> who on other Subjects touched like a Maſter, ſhould have done well to have imitated him, and when he ſpeaks of the Arrival of <hi>Armide</hi> into the Camp of the Chriſtians, if he had contented himſelf with ſaying in two or three words, that as ſoon as ſhe appeared, and that they had heard her ſpeak, they had a mind to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all to follow her, and that even the General who ought to have been more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and leſs ſenſible, was tempted by her, we ſhould then without doubt, have thought her more amiable. All that he heaps together of the Charms of Nature and of Art, gives us not ſo fair an Idæa, as that which one might form to ones ſelf, and one never fails in doing it.</p>
               <p>The graces appear but very rarely, and even when they are ſeen they will not be conſidered full-fac'd nor uncovered, it is hard to draw them well; and if one ſhould compaſs it, every one looking upon them
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:98279:54"/>
with different eyes, the Picture would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pleaſe every body.</p>
               <p>But the Sun is ſetting, and is it not time think you to retire? Let us go, ſaid the Mareſhal, and if you think it convenient we will walk a while for a little more Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:98279:55"/>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>THE FIFTH CONVERSATION.</head>
               <p>THE Mareſhal received Letters of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from <hi>Paris</hi> and from the Court, and writ thither as often to keep up the Commerce, ſhewed the Chevalier ſometimes what he had written. I cannot underſtand why people thought he was not an extraordinary perſon in that way as he was in ſpeaking. It ſeems to me, that what he writes ſhews much of a worthy well-bred man, and there is always wit in it.</p>
               <p>It is true, that there is not ſo much order and placing of words required in Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which very few mind in ſpeaking. I believe nevertheleſs, that if people did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, ſo that it ſeemed neither ſtrained nor affected, they would ſpeak much better. However, if the things that are ſaid are good ſeverally, and that there be a grace in ſpeaking them, they are well received.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98279:55"/>
But commonly that which is written muſt have a connexion, and it muſt be ſo order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that there may be no appearance that any pains was taken in obſerving it. And if any one pretend to do ſomething worth the being read; it is not enough that each piece pleaſe in it ſelf, but they muſt be made the one to fit <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and agree with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they muſt be proportionate.</p>
               <p>It is taken notice of the Mareſhal, that he loves always to be ſprightly and full of fire, and though he chiefly ſtudies to pleaſe thoſe who underſtand and judge beſt, yet he neglects not the eſteem of others. In that he reſembles thoſe Ladies, who cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure any one ſhould eſcape them: Setting aſide certain Hiſtory, ſome few Relations, and a ſmall number of Books which he hath read, he is only well verſed in the World, yet for all that he underſtands every thing. It happens alſo very often, that he improves and carries things further, which he hath but newly learned. What would a young man of ſuch parts as his come to, if he were educated by good Maſters?</p>
               <p>The Chevalier came to his houſe the next day from a Converſation that he had been at. The Mareſhal was retired into
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:98279:56"/>
his Chamber after he roſe from the Table, and ſeeing the Chevalier come in, I have very much wiſhed for you, ſaid he to him, to aſſiſt me againſt five or ſix very Learned men, who would be good company enough if they had but common ſenſe. Before we ſate down to Dinner, I ſet them diſputing, and I ſpoke in my turn; but when I thought I ſhould triumph moſt, there were two of them (if I am not miſtaken) who whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to each other, that they could not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend what it was that was thought ſo rare in me. They make me call to mind, ſaid the Chevalier, a very able man, that I knew that had read over all <hi>Taſſo</hi> with very much attention, without finding in it either Wit, or any thing to pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>One never informs ones ſelf by thoſe ſort of people, ſaid the Mareſhal, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver apprehend aright thoſe things that are ſaid to them: where there is leaſt ſenſe, there is enough for them, and any thing that is propoſed, although never ſo clear, ſeems obſcure to them. Beſides, they have a Language apart, which I underſtand not, and which would be very ill received in the World. And it ſo happens, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of coming to the knot of the buſineſs,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98279:56"/>
they divide that which you aſk them into ſo many parts, that the one puts the other out of ones mind; ſo that one remembers no longer what it was. It much delights me to ſee how they range in ſuch great or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in things that are of ſo little conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Any one that hath a juſt Wit and a true Judgment, purſues cloſely that which they hear ſpoken, or what they ſpeak them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, without varying it into ſo many forms and figures. I am pleaſed that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one in Converſation ſhould ſeek an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable diverſity and ſome little digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that they by degrees ſhould ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times raiſe themſelves, if the occaſion per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits. Though one wanders and ſoars a little too high, one may well enough re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ones ſelf: and if my Judgment may be allowed, one ought to go whitherſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ones Genius leads, without any other diviſion or diſtinction than that of good ſenſe; at leaſt this manner is more confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to our apprehenſions and thoughts, than that ſo regular Method of ſome peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who diſguiſe every thing. There is nothing in that which is natural, nor for the moſt part which is real; therefore when they breed up Children, I know not why
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98279:57"/>
they ſhould accuſtom them to ſuch imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent conſtrained Rules, which afterwards they cannot practiſe without rendring themſelves ridiculous?</p>
               <p>Study may hinder, ſaid the Chevalier, at leaſt we muſt not pretend that it will infallibly make Maſter-pieces. Nor the World neither, ſaid the Mareſhal, doth not do it always, eſpecially of thoſe people who are bred only in the Army; who commonly are not of a very pleaſing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; but in recompence of that they are ſaid to have gained Reputation and Honour, as if that would excuſe their wants in every thing elſe: we may between our ſelves ſay, that nothing is ſo great a diſhonour as to be diſagreeable and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe. It is ſomething like certain Women that pretend to Vertue, who value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves much upon their being coy and fierce; for, to prize ſo ſmall a matter ſo much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> makes me think that all is but coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit and affected, and that they are eaſier won upon, than thoſe who obſerve good Manners and Breeding, and are as affable as theſe are ſevere. The firſt ſeems to me to deſire to be thought what ſhe is not by ſome people which ſhe likes not, and with
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:98279:57"/>
whom ſhe does not deſire to ingage; the other is ſatisfied that ſhe knows her ſelf honeſt.</p>
               <p>When we judge ſincerely, ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, there is ſcarce any thing to be found that is perfect: but the more exquiſite diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment one hath, the more it is for ones honour to be indulgent, and we muſt not expect to meet with people as one would have them; but we ſhould endeavour to make them ſuch, and eſpecially if we love them, and are obliged to paſs our time with them. As for others that one ſees but by chance, they are not to be ordered as we will; they can only be a l'ttle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by telling them ſuch things as are judged moſt proper; and if they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of profiting by them, that will at the leaſt diſpoſe them to compleat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as I begin to ſpeak, ſaid the Mareſhal, you underſtand me better than I underſtand my ſelf, and whatſoever you tell me appears to me ſo eaſie to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, that I think many times I knew it before you told it. I am continually think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my Children, who cannot as yet be without me, and I love them the better
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:98279:58"/>
for it; and though Wealth be ſomething, yet I wiſh them nothing ſo much as I do Parts. We diſcourſe ſometimes of that which we think beſt for the educating of a young Prince, and by this Model, as near as it is fit for us to come to it, in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we might breed our Children. For I imagine that is one and the ſame vertue that knows how to command, if Fortune pleaſes, and how to obey, when ones duty obligeth one to it. And being ſate down with the Chevalier: You ſaid (continued he) that Study might hinder; I would gladly inform my ſelf in what manner it ſhould be uſed, for I do not believe that you are of the opinion to renounce it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely.</p>
               <p>That would be (ſaid the Chevalier) a very fantaſtical opinion, indeed the beſt natural parts of the World would be but of little value, if there were not care taken to improve and bring them to perfection. One can never take any thing aright with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having learned it; and who can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that either to do a thing well that one doth ill, or to do it better, if one doth it well, that Study can ever hinder? that is to ſay, to ſeek out the means, and that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:98279:58"/>
under the beſt Maſters; for ſo it is that one ought to ſtudy.</p>
               <p>It is ſeen by all ſorts of Exerciſes, how much Art and good Maſters are neceſſary, and it were very ſtrange, that the body ſhould be capable of inſtruction, and that the mind ſhould not be ſo to. For what like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood is there, that if Practice and good Maſters are without peradventure effectual for the making people ſkillful in riding the great Horſe, that to the making of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht perſon, they ſhould both of them be altogether needleſs and hurtful?</p>
               <p>The body and the mind are ſeldom as one could wiſh; but the defects of the body ſeem to me more difficult to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected: the mind is naturally ſouple, and it may be redreſſed, provided a right courſe be taken. And who can doubt, that if there be any one as exact in breeding Youth, as it is ſaid, <hi>Pignatel</hi> was good at Horſmanſhip, but that he might make an accompliſht man, as well as <hi>Pignatel</hi> made a good Horſe-man? How comes it about then, that it many times falls out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? The truth is, that when one learns to do a thing of an ill Maſter, one learns to do it ill; and it is much more difficult to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:98279:59"/>
chuſe good Maſters for the framing of the mind, than for the body. For the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of the body are much more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and more known than thoſe of the mind. And beſides, many people who are capable of inſtructing the mind, will not always meddle in it; for in truth, as the World judges of it, there would be but very little honour gained by undertaking the Trade, although they did acquit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of it in perfection.</p>
               <p>It is certain, that to be able, well bred, and agreeable to ſuch a degree as one would wiſh a great Prince, one cannot know too many things, ſo that he have the ſkill to make a right uſe of them, and that he knows how to value them. But to ſpeak my Judgment, it is not to be knowing, to have read very much, nor to have learned a great number of different opinions which diſcover nothing certainly. We know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing well but that which we ſee clearly, and that which we can preſently make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſee and underſtand, if they are clear-ſighted. We ſhould miſtruſt all that which we perceive but as through a Cloud, and which we cannot make very plain to the ſight of another.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:98279:59"/>
Whilſt people are young, they learn lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more than certain words which make a ſhew of Learning, though they are know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in nothing, and that is not becoming to a man that is abroad in the World. I would have one know all things, and that his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of diſcourſing might not betray his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtudied.</p>
               <p>It is a very great advantage to have an inſpection into things, ſaid the Mareſhal, and to know the World, whether it be that we are to ſpeak or write: but that which ſavours too much of Study, is for the moſt part not liked. I know not whether it be well to write as one ſpeaks, and to ſpeak as one writes. Many people have been of opinion that it is, but it ſeems to me, that the uſe is otherwiſe. 'Twere more likely, anſwered the Chevalier, if they had ſaid, that we ſhould write as we deſire to ſpeak, and ſpeak as we deſire to write; for one ſeldom doth either of them as we wiſh we could. This queſtion which is not to be deſpiſed by perſons of wit, may eaſily be cleared.</p>
               <p>We write things which are never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, and which are made only to be read, as a Hiſtory, or any ſuch like thing.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:98279:60"/>
When any one undertakes that, and would be ſucceſsful in it, they muſt not write as if they were telling a ſtory in Company: Hiſtory is more noble, and more ſevere; Converſation is more free, and negligent. And as there are ſome things which are only fit to be read, ſo there are others which are made principally to be heard ſpoken, as Harangues. If we would judge of their worth, we muſt conſider to what degree they are good when they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, ſince that is what they aim at. And becauſe that Letters are not pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced (for although they are many times read aloud) yet that is not called pronouncing, we ſhould not write them altogether as we ſpeak. As for Example, whoſoever ſhould ſee a perſon to whom he had juſt been writing a Letter, although it were very excellent, he would not ſay the ſame things to him that he had written, or at the leaſt he would not ſay them in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: yet for all that it is good when we write, to imagine in ſome ſort that we are ſpeaking, that we may not put in any thing that is not natural, or which may not be ſpoken in Company: and likewiſe when we ſpeak, to fancy that we are writing,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:98279:60"/>
that we may not ſay any thing that is not noble, and which hath not ſomething of exactneſs.</p>
               <p>How comes it to paſs, ſaid the Mareſhal, that many people are ſaid to ſpeak well, who cannot write well? It is many times believed, anſwered the Chevalier, that ſome certain perſons ſpeak well in effect, when in truth they only ſpeak well in appearance. That is becauſe either their preſence ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, or the ſound of their voice ſurpriſeth. When any one excelleth in ſpeaking, they may do the ſame in writing: it is true, that this latter requires a little more care. Alſo it ſeems to me, that one cannot write well, without knowing how to ſpeak well; but it happens, that thoſe who make it their ſtudy to write well, have commonly a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing way of ſpeaking, which is as it were almoſt ſpent. Thoſe people mind too much the ſound and harmony. This ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Language which they affect, makes them many times loſe by little and little the natural uſe of it, which conſiſts in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to every thing that one ſpeaks the motions that we feel in our hearts. For we do not ſpeak only to make our thoughts to be underſtood, but to expreſs our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:98279:61"/>
which are two very different things.</p>
               <p>He who finds himſelf not moved at any thing, is as unfit to ſpeak as he that thinks nothing. The heart hath its Language, as the Wit hath his, and this expreſſion of the heart works many times the greateſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. When the heart is not agitated, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though one hath very much wit, it touches not ſo ſenſibly; and when one is ſtirred, if the wit fails, they only make a noiſe, and ſo unſeaſonably, that they were better hold their peace. It is neceſſary then for the heart to have apprehenſions, and for the wit, not only to guide, but alſo to make the choice of them. For as there are thoughts which are agreeable, and others which are not, the very ſame diverſity is found in the motions of the heart, ſome of them are well received, and others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. You know much better than I, that to inſpire either joy or ſadneſs, and many other paſſions which govern the World (in truth to the prejudice of reaſon) it is not enough to know them by experience, but we muſt be affected with them at the ſame inſtant, at leaſt ſo as we are with thoſe things which are repreſented on the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:98279:61"/>
Whether we deſign to ſpeak well, or to write well, we muſt have many conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the well doing of it: very few people have ſucceeded. The moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult thing, in my Judgment, is to be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that which ought to pleaſe, and to have a Genius to put it in practice. I ſay in that which ought to pleaſe, becauſe it is very difficult to be aſſured of it. For in matters of agreements every one hath his ſeveral reliſh, and if you take notice of that which commonly pleaſes, it proceeds not ſo much from the perfection of it, as from a certain temperature, which agrees with our natural ſentiments. It is this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion which charms us, and it is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from whence it comes; but in my Judgment the true graces, thoſe which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect moſt, and which are always liked, are never to be without a delicateneſs, and that great things, as Pomp and Magnificence, are made not ſo much to pleaſe, as to cauſe admiration. Beauty it ſelf, when it hath ſo much luſtre, is above our ſtrength, we cannot ſupport it. We praiſe the greateſt Beauties, but we love the prettieſt: The reaſon is, becauſe we are tired with long admiring, and whatſoever is made only for
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:98279:62"/>
that, diſpleaſeth as ſoon as the admiration is over.</p>
               <p>We muſt apply our ſelves to think well, the excellency of thoughts hath ſo many advantages over other certain Beauties, they hope to find in Arts and Study, that he who thinks the beſt, is always above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I find alſo, that thoſe who have a good diſcernment in things, have likewiſe the advantage in the manner of expreſſing them, and that it is the exquiſiteneſs of the apprehenſion which makes the Language excellent. All this depends upon acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that king of Wit, which we have been ſo much ſpeaking of, and that Maſter who can teach it, may be ſaid to be an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maſter.</p>
               <p>Things of action and memory are very eaſily learned, and there are people enough to be found, who know how to teach them. But it is not ſo with that which they call to <hi>Know</hi> and to <hi>Judge:</hi> This is the Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of the mind, eſpecially as to that which regards ſkill and invention, the juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and decency of things. There are but few Maſters who do not make one take a contrary courſe, which cannot afterwards eaſily be altered. And becauſe the firſt
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:98279:62"/>
motions and impreſſions which are made in the heart of a Child take deepeſt root, and inſenſibly diſpoſeth and ſwayeth him to good or evil for his whole life; I could wiſh that ſuch Books only might be read to the young Prince, as might give him the Idæa, or at leaſt the apprehenſion of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection by ſome moſt remarkable paſſages written by a good hand. For ſometimes we ſee things ſo well hit, that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble either to ſay or think them better. One makes a great progreſs when one forms ones ſelf after ſuch models, and by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtoming ones ſelf, whatſoever one ſays hath a taſte of it.</p>
               <p>This Language which few perſons know how to ſpeak, proceeds from a juſtneſs of wit, and from an extent of underſtanding, which diſcovers things as they are. It is a natural diſcernment, which nevertheleſs we conſtantly improve, when we think of it as we ought, and frequent the company of ſuch perſons who have it by Nature. But I tell you again, Sir, that thoſe who bemoan themſelves for not having ſtudied as commonly people ſtudy, have loſt but little by it.</p>
               <p>It is no inconſiderable thing the being
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:98279:63"/>
able to undeceive ones ſelf in all things, and to know how to ſet a value upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing according to its merit: And if any one would diſcover to us, or but only make us ſenſible what we ought to believe of things, we ſhould have a great obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that perſon. Moſt people account this nothing; but for all that, it is certain, that without this knowledge we muſt be always either fool'd by our ſelves, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt to all others.</p>
               <p>It ſeems to me, ſaid the Mareſhal, that to be inſtructed how to live, and to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate ſuch opinions as one ought to have, there is nothing more to be feared than an ill Maſter. I do not wonder ſo much, that ſuch as are firſt offered, are taken for us, that is not of ſo much conſequence: But for a great Prince, upon whom the happineſs of the Publick muſt hereafter abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, and by whoſe Example ſo many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will endeavour to faſhion themſelves, as being the moſt noble Model, no care in the World ſhould be neglected. If there were a man in the fartheſt part of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> who could acquit himſelf therein bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the ableſt amongſt us, I would have him fetched. The buſineſs is to make a
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:98279:63"/>
great King, whom we may love and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire; to make him happy, and likewiſe to order it ſo, that all thoſe who live under him may be happy too. For it is but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable that thoſe ſhould a little ſhare in his happineſs, who are in duty obliged to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice themſelves for the procuring of it.</p>
               <p>There is nothing requiſite, ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, but the rendring of him an honeſt and worthy man, at leaſt that is the moſt important thing. I ſee, ſaid the Mareſhal, that this word honeſt man almoſt compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends every thing. But if any one ſhould aſk me what it is, I ſhould find my ſelf much to ſeek. I do not wonder at it, ſaid the Chevalier, for a thing of ſo large an extent, looks too many ways, and hath too many appearances and ſhadows to be expreſſed in two or three words. Thoſe who ſay that honeſty conſiſts in living and dying well, only vary the terms, without clearing the queſtion. Beſides, if one ſhould not dye, he might notwithſtanding by living be an honeſt man, nay he might by that means make a greater progreſs therein. To have a more diſtinct know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, we may look upon it in it ſelf ſeparated from all other things that are
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:98279:64"/>
not of it, or foreign to it, and conſider it by all ſorts of lights.</p>
               <p>Tell me what you believe of it, ſaid the Mareſhal, I ſhould be glad to ſee whether we have the ſame thoughts in a thing of this conſequence. I know, ſaid the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, that you muſt needs underſtand it rightly, becauſe you make uſe of it always as your guide; and if that Idæa which I have of it be good, it muſt without doubt be conformable to yours. For perfect ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty is always the ſame in what ſubjects ſoever it is found, although the difference of Time and Fortune makes it appear ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry differently. But under whatever form it ſhews it ſelf, it always pleaſeth, and by that it may principally be known; for the true Agreements come not from a ſimple ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial, or a ſlight appearance, but from a great ſtock of Wit or Merit, which min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles and ſhews it ſelf in all that one ſays, and in all the actions of ones life.</p>
               <p>It ſeems to me, that it affects not to make a myſtery of any thing, that as it avoids all extreams, it endeavours not to hide, nor to ſhew it ſelf. Its firſt appearance hath not ſo much luſtre, as either to dazle or to ſurpriſe people; but when we come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:98279:64"/>
her, we find that it hath ſo much Grace in every thing that is offered of good or ill, of ſerious or pleaſant, that one would think that all things are alike to it and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable. And if there be any parts ſo diſadvantagious, that it would be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the Graces themſelves to act them well, it knows well how to refuſe them.</p>
               <p>I find that it is not cruel, but willing to excuſe and pardon, and it is ſo far from raiſing it ſelf upon the miſery of another, that it is always ready to help thoſe that are ſo. It makes all thoſe who depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it happy, ſo far as Fortune permits; and if it be not in its power to do that, at leaſt it makes no body ſad, it is careful to avoid that even in the ſmalleſt things. If it jeſts ſometimes, its mirth and gayety tends only to the delight even of thoſe whom it makes ſport with. It is never ſo much ſatisfied with it ſelf, but that it is ſenſible that there is ſtill ſomething beyond what it can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to. it ſeeks no falſe advantages, but on the contrary, if occaſion offers not it ſelf, we muſt many times gueſs at that which is beſt in it.</p>
               <p>Its own intereſt deludes it not, and if it ſo happens, that an honeſt man be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:98279:65"/>
although his life be aimed at, he makes not uſe of all ſorts of Arguments and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to defend himſelf, but that little he ſays makes every body regret that they offended him. Repreſent to your ſelf <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, Scipio,</hi> or ſome others of that rank; for I obſerve that thoſe people are as it were above Fortune, at leaſt they are not tranſported with proſperity<hi>:</hi> and what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune ſoever attacqueth them, although they are never heard to ſay that their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue doth not forſake them, yet we may find that they have more than enough to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them. I find that honeſty always judges well, although it be very cautious in deciding; it prefers Choice before Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and hath more care of being neat and cleanly than richly dreſt; and values thoſe things that are leaſt in ſight more than thoſe that are ſoon diſcovered. Do you not take notice likewiſe, that it hath more regard to Merit than to Fortune? that it is not ſubject to be prejudiced againſt any body; that which diſorders narrow Souls ſurpriſeth it very little; and the opinion of the World hinders it not from under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the true value of things?</p>
               <p>I believe it depends but little either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:98279:65"/>
time or place; and that he who can attain ſo far as to be an honeſt worthy man in his Cottage, would be the ſame in all the the Courts of the World. But there are many things neceſſary to the being a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy honeſt man. And although ſome may paſs for ſuch at the Courts of great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we muſt not therefore conclude, that there is nothing wanting in them, unleſs they can be ſo every where, and amongſt all ſorts of people.</p>
               <p>Many obſervations might be made, if any one would enlarge upon this Subject. But to conclude, 'tis obſerved, that hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty hath this in it, it leaves a kind and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der remembrance always of it ſelf in thoſe who have once known it, and carries it ſelf ſo, that every body is very glad to have obliged it.</p>
               <p>But now after all this, a Lady who was perfectly handſom, and of ſo pleaſing a wit and humour, that even the handſomeſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies could not chuſe but love her, aſked me what an honeſt man was, and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Woman; for the expreſſion is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to both: and when I told her my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of it, and that ſhe her ſelf had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed very rationally of it, ſhe confeſſed
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:98279:66"/>
that ſhe thought all that which I told her was very neceſſary for the being that which ſhe had aſked. But yet there was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more which was unexplainable, and was better known by practice than by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, which, as ſhe imagined, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in I knew not what of Nobleneſs, that heightens all the good Qualities, and which proceeds only from the heart and from the mind, the reſt is only the Train and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page of it.</p>
               <p>This Lady, ſaid the Mareſhal, was very hard to be pleaſed; for there was enough before for the making an honeſt man, and I approve without exception of all that you have obſerved concerning it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be that which you ſaid of pleaſing, and that it was an infallible proof of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty. It ſeems to me, that people very often ſucceed in that, as well by ill ways as by good, nay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and with more choice and ſplendour. To that, ſaid the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, one may anſwer in two words, that there are ſome perſons who underſtand true Merit, and that it is a good ſign when one pleaſeth them<hi>:</hi> But there are many more who judge not well, and for thoſe we have no great cauſe to rejoyce when
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:98279:66"/>
we are ſo agreeable to them.</p>
               <p>Howſoever it be, ſaid the Mareſhal, to examine honeſty well, whether we conſider it in it ſelf, or in thoſe things that it ſays and that it doth, it ſtill appears to be above every thing elſe, and there is nothing ſo worthy of a great Prince. It is true, ſaid the Chevalier, that it is amiable, and that it inſpires reſpect, although it be forced to be ſilent and unactive; but you have hit upon the two things which give luſtre, the ſpeaking and the actions, all depend upon that, and it was that (ſays <hi>Homer)</hi> which the Learned <hi>Chiron</hi> taught to young <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Maſter, ſaid the Mareſhal, without doubt had great ſkill, he made a Scholar that the World hath talked of<hi>:</hi> and if that we ſee ſo few of ſo high and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary a Worth, it muſt needs be the fault of the Governors. As he ended theſe words, he ſaw Gameſters come in, who came to divert him, and that put an end to the Converſation.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:98279:67"/>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>THE SIXTH CONVERSATION.</head>
               <p>THE Chevalier came to the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals houſe, who had paſſed the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon at play. He came juſt as the Game was ended, and the Gameſters were retiring. The Mareſhal, who had a mind to go abroad, was glad to ſee him come ſo opportunely to have him with him. I will not aſk you, ſaid he, whether you are for walking; for I know very well you love to look upon the different colours which are in the Sky, when the Sun ſets, and that it is a pleaſure to you to breathe the freſh Air in the Evening. I am only in doubt of which ſide we ſhould go. That Wood where we were the other day would pleaſe me much; but we muſt croſs the Town to go to it, and the way is very rough. I doubt beſides, whether we ſhall have time enough. I ſuppoſe, ſaid the Chevalier, that it will be beſt to go the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:98279:67"/>
lower way along by the Water-ſide: which advice was followed, and they went on that ſide as far as to the end of the Meadow, where they ſtopt (becauſe they could not go further with the Coach) and alighted to walk by the River ſide.</p>
               <p>The Mareſhal loved not to be long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and it happened luckily for him, and for thoſe who frequent him, who were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways glad to hear him. He had been ſo imployed at play, that he had ſcarce ſaid any thing all the day. He began at the firſt to ſpeak of ſome things which he had moſt a mind to, and after ſome diſcourſe upon that Subject: We muſt not, ſaid he, look upon Kings with the ſame eyes as we do upon private perſons, the moſt part where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of have little other aim than to live con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly and at eaſe, though a man of abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity doth always ſtudy moſt how to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe love and eſteem.</p>
               <p>I know very well what falſe glory is (a worthy honeſt man regards it not, and the wiſeſt deſpiſe it) but it ſeems to me, that the more Courage and Wit a man hath, the more he loves true Honour: and if there where any one who could not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that, although he hath all other
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:98279:68"/>
things to be wiſhed, he would neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs be much to be pitied, at leaſt if he were of a generous noble Nature; and if you obſerve it, people are leſs willing to pardon thoſe injuries, which touch upon their Honour than any other. And when they find themſelves touched on that ſide, they think they cannot enough reſent it. Alſo to ſay the truth, that which makes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> people ſo much deſire great Imployments and high Commands, is not for the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies of life; for our lives are made by them the more troubleſom, but it is the hopes of having an opportunity to make it appear, that they have Merit in them.</p>
               <p>But this nevertheleſs for a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot extend it ſelf far, nor be but of ſhort continuance. But Kings are looked upon by all the Earth, and Poſterity which never flatters any body, will be Judge of their Merit. Glory is their greateſt and their chiefeſt Intereſt. All the Heroes and all the great Men have devoted and given themſelves up to it. One had need be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, faithful, and zealous to give them good counſel, in this particular, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally they ought well to underſtand in what true Glory conſiſts, and by what
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:98279:68"/>
means it may be acquired.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, that <hi>Parmenio</hi> (that great Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain, whoſe only aim was to vanquiſh) counſelled his Maſter to ſurprize the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, becauſe of their great number, and to aſſault them by the favour of the night. But this Prince (who made it not ſo much his aim to gain the Battel, as to make his Valour be admired) would fight them in the day time, being reſolved to loſe all, both his Life and Fortune, rather than to run the hazard of having cauſe to bluſh at his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. The ſame man counſelled him alſo to divide <hi>Aſia</hi> with the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive great Treaſures, which they propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to him. This advice he received no better than the other; he had a heart too Imperious to ſuffer any one to be equal with him, and too high to love Gold and Riches. His deſire tended only to glory, and if he did not always know what was the beſt and moſt ſolid, it was becauſe he was yery young, and that he ſaw himſelf at the top of Fortune. Beſides, he graſped at ſo many things, that he could not well have a due regard to every thing that he undertook, and he was alſo eaſily tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:98279:69"/>
The ſmalleſt errours that Princes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, are ſometimes of great conſequence to their reputation; and I ſhould adviſe them (if they would truſt my Judgment) to conſider often in what manner the greateſt Men would carry themſelves, if they had their parts to act.</p>
               <p>It is no ill way to adviſe a Prince to do that which is moſt honeſt, and likewiſe moſt heroick. We have ſeen already, that it is that which befits him beſt; and if we look further into things concerning this World, we ſtill find in all manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, that this at laſt is the beſt. Both Heaven and Fortune ſeem to have a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular care of theſe great hearts who are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent and reſign up themſelves. The braveſt for the moſt part prevail, and an high reſolution hath been the ſaving of many more people than it hath loſt. The more this Prince, whom I was ſpeaking of, ſought after death, the further it was from him; and if he were wounded (as it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible for any one to throw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf continually into danger, and never to be ſo) it was at leaſt without being ever killed or overcome.</p>
               <p>However it is not to be wiſhed, that a
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:98279:69"/>
Prince ſhould hazard himſelf ſo much, or that he ſhould only know that way to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for (beſides that it would put us in continual Alarms for ſo precious a life) it appears to me below a great Prince, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf on all occaſions<hi>:</hi> and if you well conſider it, it is not that which moſt ſhews the greatneſs of ones Soul, and the contempt of death. I think it much better to march towards death with a ſteddy pace, like <hi>Socrates,</hi> than to precipitate ones ſelf upon it, like <hi>Alexander;</hi> for this is to effect a very difficult thing very eaſily, which ſhews a heart to be more firm and reſolute.</p>
               <p>There are ſome Soveraigns, who we can look on only but as wiſe Politicians, and that in my mind is not the beſt form that they might appear in. Something which I cannot expreſs, of more noble, would give them a greater ſplendour, and can you think any thing more worthy of a great Prince than Love and Arms? They are the Subject of the fineſt Romances, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Chevalier, and when a Reign is at an end without either Love or Arms, a Hiſtory has but a few things to ſay. But ſome Princes are not born to act both parts,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:98279:70"/>
and it is always enough for a Soveraign to govern his States well, and to render his Subjects happy.</p>
               <p>I have known ſome Princes, ſaid the Mareſhal, who would have been very gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant men, if there had been care taken at the firſt, to have put them into the right way, and to have ſhewed them what was to be done. This firſt point of Education is of much greater importance to them than private perſons; for when they are no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger under the Conduct of a Governour, all that they do is approved on, or at leaſt it is ſo in appearance, and no body comes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their preſence, but with a deſign to pleaſe them, becauſe although one loves them, yet one eaſily inclines to love their favour more: And in truth it would be great imprudence for any one to hazard the drawing the hatred of his Prince upon himſelf, and to go about to adviſe him as he would one of his particular Friends, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he had firſt ſignified his pleaſure to have it ſo. However thoſe perſons who are near about him, if they are not too much ſwayed by Intereſt, may very ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell him in an agreeable manner, all that which may contribute to his Glory and to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:98279:70"/>
his Happineſs. It is an eaſie matter, ſaid the Chevalier, to give them good advice as to their glory. It is agreed what that is, and how it may be acquired; all thoſe who know how to judge will concur. But it is not ſo as to ones happineſs, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends more upon the temper than upon thoſe things which people believe give it. And to ſay the truth, whoſoever under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to aſcertain a Prince what will make him happy, muſt know him very perfectly. Many times we our ſelves know not what would be beſt for our own happineſs.</p>
               <p>You ſpeak reaſon, ſaid the Mareſhal, but when all things that can be wiſhed preſent themſelves, and that there is nothing want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but to chuſe well, it ſeems to me, that with a very little help, it were no difficult thing to be happy. And to ſay the truth, he is in a fair way to it, who ſees himſelf one of the firſt among the Maſters of the World. Fortune hath nothing greater to give. Let us conſider what pleaſure it is to do good: There is nothing in my mind more noble, and this delight ſeems to me to be made only for great Princes; the more favour they beſtow, the more they are in a condition to grant: For it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:98279:71"/>
that their gifts, which are accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with choice and eſteem, ſupport their Grandeur, and render them the more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful. It is not riches that are principally to be deſired from Kings (for their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuries might be exhauſted by profuſeneſs) but it is Imployments and Truſts, theſe are the opportunities, by which men make it appear what they are; and when thoſe perſons who have Worth, are put into Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments ſuitable to themſelves, they make themſelves known, and their Princes are well ſerved.</p>
               <p>That which commonly they want, and which we have abundantly, is the pleaſures which you know we have in converſing freely with thoſe we love, and the being in a condition to diſpute of certain advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, in which neither Fortune nor Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs have any part. The price of Merit, which touches ſo much many brave hearts, at length becomes inſenſible to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe people praiſe indifferently all that they do alike, without regarding either meaſure or decency. One muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placent, as becomes a gallant man, to make his life agreeable; and I cannot conceive that thoſe Princes of the <hi>Levant,</hi> who live
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:98279:71"/>
only amongſt Slaves, can be happy. They have all things, and perfectly enjoy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; they have the faireſt Women in the World, but they are Captives, always in priſon, without wit or love<hi>:</hi> they have nothing of that which is moſt taking, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of freedom, nothing that is pleaſant and delightful.</p>
               <p>The Commerce of Love and the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of gallant Adventures, which make one delight in the Courts of the World, and to endeavour to render ones ſelf an accompliſht man, all this is unknown to them. They are only ſavage Events which they delight in. I am thinking of that which you ſaid juſt now; there are always in thoſe Countries ſome Adventures of Love and of War, but they are ſuch, that I defie <hi>Arioſto, Taſſo,</hi> and even <hi>Sapho,</hi> to make a pleaſant Romance of them. If li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo be happineſs, that felicity ſeems to me very barbarous, and I cannot believe, that any man of good ſenſe can envy it. The greateſt pleaſures, if people know not how to manage them, and that there be not wit intermixt with them, or ſome ſenſe of Honour, laſt not long, and that may be ſome comfort to thoſe who have not all that they deſire.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:98279:72"/>
I look upon it, that theſe Princes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe rather than exalt themſelves, in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting ſuch a Grandeur, which no body hath any thoughts of diſputing with them. I think that Civility and Majeſty both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which makes people find with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that ſuch Princes are their Maſters, is much better; the more they condeſcend, the more one is ready to ſubmit, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe that are well bred perſons, who never preſume too much.</p>
               <p>I think that the moſt eminent men were wont to communicate freely with their Friends, and that they were very familiar, at leaſt <hi>Cæſar</hi> was ſo, ſaid the Chevalier, even with his Souldiers, ſo far as he took delight, to remember in any of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable ſayings, this familiarity. Which to ſay the truth, accompanied with other kindneſſes, had charmed them ſo, that when they were to fight for his Glory, they thought nothing difficult to them, and were not apprehenſive either of peril or death. If by chance they were made Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and had their lives offered them, they refuſed it, and ſaid, that it belonged to the Souldiers of <hi>Cæſar</hi> to give, not to take Quarter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:98279:72"/>
I wonder not then at all, ſaid the Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal, that ſuch a man followed by ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, although the ſmaller number did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways conquer<hi>:</hi> That which I ſaid, that Heaven takes theſe great hearts into its protection, it appears alſo in this Hero, who amidſt all thoſe Combates, in which he was very active, received not the leaſt hurt.</p>
               <p>Princes of great Deſigns and high En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes, ſaid the Chevalier, are always beloved; although Fortune, which we know is inconſtant, leaves their ſide, yet Glory &amp; Honour never forſake them. <hi>Cæſar</hi> was of this number, he had nothing in him which was not noble, and which ſavoured not of Grandeur. He was ſo brave, and ſo full of curteſie both together, that he would have hazarded his perſon to have ſaved the meaneſt of his Souldiers. He lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all thoſe that followed his Fortune. He ſhared with them the glory, as he did the danger. And it was without doubt the ſureſt way to gain, as he did, fifty Battels, without loſing one, firſt to gain their love and eſteem.</p>
               <p>A few days before that great fight, wherein the <hi>Almans</hi> and the people of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:98279:73"/>
                  <hi>North</hi> were defeated, he had ſent Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours to their Prince <hi>Arioviſtus,</hi> who contrary to the Law of Nations detained them, and put them in Chains. <hi>Cæſar</hi> ſaid that he was not more glad of gaining the Victory, than he was to embrace them, and knock off their Fetters. But this that I am about to tell you, ſhews much of his nature, and to what degree he was belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Curio,</hi> who was one of his Generals, was making War in another corner of the World. He was a young Man of a great Courage, but of little Experience, and had to deal with the <hi>Africans,</hi> who were grown old in the Trade. This young Man being fallen into an Ambuſcade, and finding it was in his power to ſave himſelf; but that he had not had prudence or good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune enough to ſecure the Troops which <hi>Cæſar</hi> had committed to his truſt, he choſe rather to dye than to preſent himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. Every word that <hi>Cæſar</hi> ſaid of his Friend, ſeemed to be accompanied with ſighs and tears. Neither was it the fear of an ill reception or uſage, which made <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio</hi> take ſo deſperate a courſe; but it was a certain apprehenſion which makes us fear
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:98279:73"/>
the ſight of our Friends, when they are of ſo high a Merit, and that we are ſenſible they have no reaſon to approve of our actions.</p>
               <p>We are apt to leſſen peoples Merit, according as we love or hate the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (ſaid the Mareſhal) and <hi>Cæſar</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood very well how to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be loved. I remember the Borders of <hi>Lignon,</hi> where I delighted my ſelf ſo much when I was young, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Oracle,</p>
               <q>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ameris, ama.</q>
               <p>This is a very ſure way, at leaſt if it be performed handſomly. For it is not enough to devote ones ſelf to gain people: the principal Secret conſiſts in managing it ſo, that the perſon whom one loves, ſhould be glad of it. The manner of doing it, which ſeems not to be ſo conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, imports more than all the reſt, and I ſee that the craftieſt are taken with it as well as the ſimpleſt; but I hardly remember where I leſt off.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:98279:74"/>
You need not take much care for that, ſaid the Chevalier, for you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leave a Subject, but thoſe who have heard you are very well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with that which you have ſaid. Beſides, a little of negligence is very convenient, (could one live eaſie with people who are ſo very exact and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular) but I think you were ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Cæſar,</hi> and I was thinking, I remember, that the moſt eloquent man of thoſe times told him one day, that he had done more than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered his Enemies, for he had van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed Victory her ſelf. And that he had ſet himſelf above her, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning all thoſe who had a mind to ruine him. This commendation which was ſo juſtly due to him, gives me a great Idæa of him; but there is one thing of him, which angers me much, that is, his calling of us <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians.</hi> I am not the only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſuffers this injury with impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience: it hath ſo diſſatisfied one of our Romance-makers, that without any difficulty, he writ that <hi>Cæſar</hi> was
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:98279:74"/>
no Courtier. Upon my faith I am glad of it, ſaid the Mareſhal, and it was but what he deſerved; for what made him uſe our Anceſtors ſo ill?</p>
               <p>However, ſaid the Chevalier, this reproach which hath made you laugh, is not ſo ill grounded, that it may not be maintained, and without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining what it is to be a Chevalier in that manner that we underſtand it. People are always more ſo at the Court of a Prince, than in a Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. Alſo it ſeems to me, that the Manners of Cities, and their ways of doing things are not noble; you know that the great World cannot ſuffer them. That which ſavours of the Country-ſavageneſs may be noble, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though far different from the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Courts. That is becauſe there is to be diſcerned I know not what of Worth and Greatneſs, plain and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Art. Imagine to your ſelf thoſe thick dark Foreſts of <hi>Africa,</hi> the infinite number of Lyons, and many other wild Beaſts, all this appears to me
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:98279:75"/>
more noble than the Gardens of the Grand Signor.</p>
               <p>That which you were ſaying but now interrupted the Mareſhal, makes me call to mind, that it is not enough when one ſpeaks, or when one takes a Journey, to know to what place one would go, nor to take the right way to it; but one muſt think how to make the Journey as pleaſant and eaſie to us as we can.</p>
               <p>To return to <hi>Cæſar,</hi> people held that he was the greateſt Man in the World, and I believe, if we conſider him every way, there is reaſon for it, as well for the Wonders of his Life and Fortune, as for the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Wit and Vertue. Is it not he who ſo long time ſince gave the example and invention of all thoſe extraordinary things, that are at this day practiſed in War? Might we not be able to know yet little better what kind of man he was; for they ſpeak differently of him.</p>
               <p>It is very difficult, anſwered the Chevalier, to judge rightly of thoſe
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:98279:75"/>
whom we have not ſeen, and who have lived in an Age ſo remote. But if it were poſſible to diſcover and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold a man ſo far back, and truly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine him, certainly it muſt be <hi>Cæſar.</hi> He hath done ſo many things, and his life (though full of variety) is ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, that there is ſeen ſome corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence in all his actions, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the cauſes of it may eaſily be diſcovered. It may alſo be ſaid, that crafty people had obſerved him, who talked very boldly and freely of him to one another. One of the cleareſt ſighted men of thoſe times (but one perhaps alſo, who was unreaſonably fond of the Laws of his Town and Country) ſaid, that never any man better underſtood Juſtice, nor had been more unjuſt than <hi>Cæſar.</hi> This ſhews on the one ſide, that he had a good diſcernment of things, but as to the reſt, he ſlighted thoſe common Vertues.</p>
               <p>That which makes me know ſo much of his Spirit, and his Actions, is the Writings which he hath left (at leaſt
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:98279:76"/>
if it be his own) for there is a very Learned man who would perſwade me, that it was not his. Whoſe then, ſaid the Mareſhal? Of a certain, I know not who, anſwered the Chevalier. I believe for all that, it had been more eaſie for this certain I know not, who to have conquered and rendred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter, than to have written in that noble Style. You know that in matter of Conqueſt, happy Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions may help very much: 'twas ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be <hi>Cæſar</hi> to expreſs ones ſelf in that manner, and chance hath nothing to do in it. His Merit and his Greatneſs is ſeen in the ſmalleſt things that he ſays, not that he ſpeaks in <hi>Pompeys</hi> words, on the contrary. His way is plain, without Ornament; but hath in it a pureneſs and nobleneſs, not eaſily expreſſed, which proceeds from a good Education, and from the height of his Genius.</p>
               <p>Theſe Maſters of the World who are, as it were above Fortune, look with indifferency upon the moſt of thoſe things, which we admire, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:98279:76"/>
becauſe they are but little affected with them, they ſpeak but ſlightly of them. In a place where he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating how two or three of his Legions were for ſome time in diſorder, fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt thoſe of <hi>Pompeys; People believed,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that there would have been an end of</hi> Cæſar, <hi>if</hi> Pompey <hi>had known how to overcome, that Victory had decided the</hi> Roman <hi>Empire.</hi> You ſee in how few and plain words he expreſſes a thing of ſo great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cæſar</hi> was born with too violent paſſions, Glory and Love, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him away like two Torrents. Thoſe infinite numbers of Deſigns which he had laid from his infancy even to the end of his life, (for he was of a very active Spirit) tended only to them. Not but that he had other ſentiments, which you know make people deſire the ſociety of men, and take delight in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. For to be an accompliſht man, as <hi>Cæſar</hi> was, one muſt take part in all things that may render ones life
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:98279:77"/>
happy. But theſe two paſſions tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported him, he was not very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly touched or concerned at any thing, but only ſo far as it might be of advantage for his main Deſigns, the ends before-mentioned; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had been ſo famous in the Wars, he loved it not ſo much for it ſelf, as that he might thereby ſeat him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above all.</p>
               <p>He was liberal and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, fierce, but not revengeful, and as to that great injuſtice, which peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple blame him for, and lay as a ſtain upon ſo fair a life, it may be ſaid in two words, that he who was of all the <hi>Romans</hi> fitteſt to govern, had a mind alone to do that well which ſo many others did ill.</p>
               <p>He was tall, of a reaſonable ſhape, handſom, of a good Meen, dexterous in all Exerciſes of Arms, and a good Horſe-man. He had a fair Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion, and ſmooth, black Eyes, quick and cunning. He had a ſtrong and piercing Voice, and a great Grace in ſpeaking. He was of a delicate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:98279:77"/>
as the moſt part of thoſe are who are of that kind of Wit and Temper. It is ſaid, that he gained health by neglecting it; and that he uſed ſo much Exerciſe, that he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred himſelf by it indefatigable.</p>
               <p>He had Miſtreſſes in all parts where he came, at <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> and amongſt the <hi>Gauls.</hi> He was as it were enchanted in <hi>Egypt;</hi> for what was it he undertook not for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of that Country? And further up in <hi>Africa,</hi> was he not again in Love with a Black-a-more Queen? His aim was at Ladies of the higheſt Quality: I know not whether it were becauſe that the Behaviour of men added more grace to their natural Beauty, or that a ſenſe of Glory joyned with Love, made him look upon Ladies as a kind of Conqueſt. He affected a little, perhaps, too much to be talked of; but I do not pretend to repreſent him as a man without failings; for who is it that can boaſt himſelf to be without any? but I ſpeak of him as an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Conqueror, and of immenſe natural parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:98279:78"/>
In the moſt hazardous and hotteſt Actions of the Wars, he alone was the joy and hopes of his Army. They all believed him ſo able and ſo reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, that they deſpaired of nothing under his Conduct; and with that he had a certain gayety, which ſparkled in his eyes, and on his face, which animated them on all occaſions. And if they were at any time in doubt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the event of things, it was only their care for him; for few cared for ſurviving him themſelves.</p>
               <p>He loved fine Cloaths, and his rich Dreſs made him always to be known, and principally on a day of Battel. He would have his Souldiers to be neatly attired, and always ready<hi>:</hi> and in my mind it is a great ſign that thoſe ſort of people have honours in them, when they love to have a good Equipage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to be very curious and neat in their Arms. He regarded not whether his men were of great ſtature or no. That, ſaid the Mareſhal, depends upon fancy: there are many who are not very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing, yet who make themſelves to be
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:98279:78"/>
taken notice of enough. This great man was never miſtaken in any thing; and I admire that he was a Prodigy both in Wit and Valour.</p>
               <p>I ſhould not be ſurpriſed at an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Valour in a Brute, all perſons who know neither pleaſure nor pain, and who are not ſenſible what it is to be dead or alive. But for a man of ſo ſenſible a temper, and ſo delicate, and of ſo ſubtil and high Underſtanding, that it is in truth which ſeems rare to me. It is indeed, ſaid the Chevalier; but for all that we muſt only wonder at the greatneſs of his Wit. For although one may find ones ſelf very ſenſible of pain, and cannot make it eaſie to our ſelves to dye, yet when one hath a courage firm and reſolute to a certain degree, and that is no hard matter to have, one may be as brave as one hath a mind to be; one may manage ones life or abandon it as one judges beſt, and as occaſion requires. There needs but an ordinary firmneſs to make one reſolve indifferently either way,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:98279:79"/>
and <hi>Cæſar</hi> had always Glory before him, which made him chuſe that which was moſt becoming a Hero. I had not conſidered nor examined him in this way, ſaid the Mareſhal, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that you are in the right.</p>
               <p>They were till night by the River ſide, ſometimes ſitting, ſometimes walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and always diſcourſing of many things; but Hiſtorians never relate all.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98279:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
